<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: learning | curious and driven]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/learning/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-19T21:48:41-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nutrition for Health: Cancer]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/07/17/july-17-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/07/17/july-17-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Plan:</p>

<ul>
<li><s>Week 4 of Nutrition for Health: Cancer</s> almost, 3 videos left for tomorrow</li>
<li><s>Justice 9: Markets and Morals about Surrogate motherhood</s></li>
<li><s>Justice Quiz 2</s> 4 from 5.</li>
<li>Karamazov's almost at finish line</li>
</ul>


<hr />

<p><strong>Cancer</strong></p>

<h2>Statistics</h2>

<p>Rank | Cancer | New cases dx 2008 (1000s) | % all cancer</p>

<p>1|Lung|1608|12.7</p>

<p>2|Breast| 1384| 10.9</p>

<p>3|Colorectum| 1235 | 9.8</p>

<p>4| Stomach | 989 | 7.8</p>

<p>5| Prostate | 899 | 7.1</p>

<p>6| Liver | 750 | 5.9</p>

<p>Cancer is a multi-factorial disease state. <em>One of the three cancer cases can be prevented</em> throught simple lifestyle changes.</p>

<p>New American Plate is recommend 2/3 of vegetables, fruits, whole grains, beans and 1/3 or less of animal protein.</p>

<ul>
<li>fruits and vegietables at least 5 a day</li>
<li>keep your salt down (no more than 5 g, salt is 40% sodium)</li>
<li>stay out of the red meat, like beef, pork, lamb, bacon and sausages</li>
<li>stay out of sugar soft drinks</li>
<li>fiber is good for the gut</li>
<li>be physucally active for 30 minutes a day</li>
<li>know your limits with alcohol</li>
<li>love your skin</li>
<li>stop smoke</li>
<li>healthy weight range</li>
</ul>


<h2>Diet and Cancer</h2>

<ul>
<li><strong>body fatness</strong></li>
<li><strong>physical activity</strong></li>
<li><strong>food and drink promote weight gain</strong></li>
<li>plant foods</li>
<li>limit alcohol drink</li>
<li>dietary supplements</li>
<li>breastfeeding</li>
</ul>


<p>Corelations between GDP and obesity.</p>

<h2>Plant foods</h2>

<ul>
<li>eat at leat 5 servings (400 g) of non-starchy fruits and vegetables per day</li>
<li>eat relatively unprocessed cereals (grains)</li>
<li>limit refined starchy foods</li>
</ul>


<h2>Antioxidants</h2>

<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th>Nutrition </th>
<th> Cancer Site</th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td>Fruits and nonstrachy vegetables </td>
<td> Lung, mouth, pharynx, larynx, esophagus, stomach</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>


<p>Caretonoid-containing foods | Lung, mouth, pharynx, esophagus</p>

<p>Tomato products | Prostate</p>

<p>Allium veg (onion, garlic) | Stomach, colon, rectum</p>

<p>Vitamin C-containing foods | Esophagus</p>

<p>Folate-containing foods | Pancreas</p>

<p>Fiber-containing foods | Colon, rectum</p>

<p>Milk and calcium supplements | Colon, rectum</p>

<p>High PA | Colon, postmenopausal breast, endometrium</p>

<p><em>Phytochemicals</em> in fruits, vegetables, beans, grains and plants.</p>

<ul>
<li>beta carotene</li>
<li>ascorbic acid (vitamine C)</li>
<li>vitomine E</li>
<li>folice acid</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Isoflavones</em> found in soy products, red clover, garbanzo beans and licorice, lignans in flaxseed and whole grains.
<em>Phytoestrogens</em> may play a role in development of and protection against certain hormone-dependent types of cancer: breast, prostate.</p>

<p>Broccoli, brussels sprouts, cabbage, cauliflower, teas help rid body of harmful free radicals. Free radicals can damage call's DNA, trigger some types of cancer and other chronic disease.</p>

<p><em>Anthocyanidins</em> found in grapes, eggplant, red cabbage, redishes, may act as antioxidants, may protect agains some cancer and hear disease.</p>

<p><em>Quercetin</em> found in apples, onions, teas, red wine.</p>

<p><em>Ellagic acid</em> found in raspberries, blackberries, cranberries, strawberries, walnuts.</p>

<p><em>Carotenoids</em> carrots, yams, cantoloupe, squash, apricots.</p>

<p><em>Lycopene</em> cooked tomatoes, red peppers, pink grapefruit</p>

<p><em>Lutin and zeaxanthin</em> spinach, kale, turnip greens.</p>

<p><em>Allyl sulfides</em> found in garlic, onions. May stimulate enzymes that help eliminate harmful chemicals from body. May strengthen immune system.</p>

<h2>Colorectal Cancer and Diet</h2>

<ul>
<li>convincing: red meat and processed meat</li>
<li>convincing: excess body fat, stomach</li>
<li>convincing: excess alcohol intake in males</li>
<li>probable: excess alcohol intake in females</li>
<li>convincing: physical activity reduces risk</li>
</ul>


<p>prevent 45% if follow lifestyle, diet.</p>

<h2>Meat consumption</h2>

<ul>
<li>1999: 218 million tons annual, global</li>
<li>2030: 376 million tons annually predicted</li>
</ul>


<p>Consumption of red and processed meat has been associated with increased risk colorectal cancer. Limit &lt;500 g peer week.</p>

<ul>
<li>Heme iron in red meat</li>
<li>Carcinogens formed during high heat cooking</li>
<li>Nitres in meat</li>
</ul>


<h2>Fiber and Colon Cancer</h2>

<p>10% risk reduction in colorectal cancer for each 10 grams of fiber eaten per day.</p>

<h2>Calcium</h2>

<p>Decreased risk particularly pronounced in colorectal cancer. Risk decresed up to 1300 mg/day.</p>

<h2>Exercise</h2>

<p>5 times per week had 20% lower risk colon cancer than men who rarely/never exercised. 20% higher risk for men who watched TV or videos for 5-6 hours a day than men who watched less than 3 hours.</p>

<h2>Prostate Cancer and Diet</h2>

<ul>
<li>second most common cancer in men</li>
<li>14% of all new cancer in men (2008)</li>
<li>1 in 6 men in US will be diagnosed in lifetime</li>
<li>median age is 72</li>
<li>African American, Caribbean, Australia</li>
<li>family history</li>
<li>diet</li>
<li>lack of exercises</li>
<li>obesity</li>
<li>genetics</li>
</ul>


<p>Diet high in <em>lycopene</em> could prevent 11% of prostate cancer in US/year. Recommends eating at least 5 portions a day of fruits and vegetables.</p>

<p><em>Selenium</em> supplement use reduces prostate cancer risk (overall evidence on supplements and cancer is inconsistent). In plant food, soil content, brazil nuts, oatmeal, some animal food.</p>

<p>Calcium, milk and dairy, processed meat could increase the risk. Legumes including soy and food with vitamin E could reduce risk as well as cruciferous vegetables and omega-3 fatty acid intake.</p>

<h2>Nutrition Impact of Prostate Cancer</h2>

<ul>
<li>radical prostatectomy</li>
<li>cryotherapy</li>
<li>radiation</li>
<li>hormonal therapy</li>
</ul>


<p>Selenium (200 mg/d) and Vitamin E (400 IU/day) no lower of prostate cancer versus placebo.</p>

<p>2 glasses nonfat milk per day had 23% > risk prostate cancer. IGF-1 levels had 39% higher risk of prostate cancer than those with lowels levels.</p>

<p>1500-2000 mg calcium/day had 87% hight risk of fatal prostate cancer compared to those who gat less than 750 mg/day. Risk was 2.5 times hight for those 2000 mg/day.</p>

<h2>Summary recommendations</h2>

<ul>
<li>selenium 55 mcg</li>
<li>vitamin E 33 IU</li>
<li>calcium 1200 mg</li>
<li>zinc 11 mg</li>
<li>consume cooked tomatoes or tomato sauces</li>
</ul>


<h2>Breast Cancer and Diet</h2>

<p>Risk:</p>

<ul>
<li>age</li>
<li>alcohol in any form</li>
<li>breastfeeding your baby may decrease both pre and post menopausal breast cancer risk</li>
<li>family history (5-10%)</li>
<li>inactivity</li>
<li>weight</li>
</ul>


<p>Those with breast cancer in immediate family but who had <em>breasfeed</em> developed only 41% as many cancers as those with family member with cancer but didn't breastfeed. Breastfeeding from 2 to 6 months.</p>

<p><em>Soy food</em> do not increase any cancer risk, may even help lower risk (not proven). General guidelines are to avoid soy supplements.</p>

<p><em>Fiber</em> 5% reduction in breast cancer for each additional 10 grams fiber per day consumed. Inverse association between dietary fiber intake and breast cancer risk.</p>

<p><em>Calcium</em> recommended dose 1500 mg calcium, 400-800 IU vitamin D per day.</p>

<p><em>38% could be prevent</em> - maintain healthy weight, physical active, drink less alcohol, breastfeed the baby.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>Justice</strong></p>

<p>Egg donor from a woman who was intelenget, athletic, 5"10', 1400 SAT. $50k</p>

<p>Sperm - $70.</p>

<p><em>Egg or sperm should or not to sold for money?</em></p>

<p>Mrs. Stern met Mary 29, surrogate mother. They've made a deal, 10k$ in exchange AI with Stern sperm and give the baby to the Sterns.</p>

<p>Objections to enforcing surrogacy contracts:
- tainted (испорчен, запятнан) constent 1) coercion 2) lack of information.
- dehumanizing</p>

<p>Court said the contract is enforceable. NJ supremecourt said ths contract is uneforceable:</p>

<p>Under the contract the natural motther is irrevocably committed before she know the strength of her bond with her child. She never makes a truly voluntary, informed decision, for any decision prior to the baby's birth is, in the most important sense, uninformed.</p>

<p>This is the sale of a child, or, the very least, the sale of a mother's right to her child... Whatever idealism may motivate the participants, the profit motive predomintates, permeates, and ultimately governs the transaction.</p>

<p>Emotionals bond to the child.</p>

<p><strong>Mill's Utilitarianism</strong></p>

<p>Respect people rights is a way of making everybody better of in the long run.</p>

<p>Strong theory of rights that says individual matter not just as instruments to be used for a larger social purpose or for the sake of maximazing utility, individuals are separate beings with separate lives worthy of respect.</p>

<p><em>Liberarianism</em> takes individual rights seriosly, because it say the fundemntal individual right is the right to liberty. Because we are separate humans we have individual right to libery, and that means the right to choose freely to live our lives as we please provided with respect other people's rights.</p>

<blockquote><p>Inviduals have rights so strong and far-reaching are these rights that they raise the quiestion of what, if anything the state may do. Robert Nozick</p></blockquote>

<h2>The Libertarian view of goverment</h2>

<ol>
<li>No Paternalist Legislation (that's passing laws that protect people from themselves, seatbelt for example)</li>
<li>No Morals Legislation (moral values of the society, gays and lesbians)</li>
<li>No Redistribution of income from rich to poor.</li>
</ol>


<p><strong>Nozick</strong>: What makes income distribution just?</p>

<ol>
<li>Justice in Acquisition (initial holdings, did people get the things they use to get their money fairly, ex. stole factory, land)</li>
<li>Justice in Transfer (free choice buying and selling things, free market)</li>
</ol>


<p>Nozick agrees that taxation is theft</p>

<p>Taxation = taking of earnings, in other words it means taking the fruits of my labor, but if the state has a right to take my earnings or the fruits of my labor.</p>

<p><em>Taking of earnings = forced labor.</em> Because forced labor involves in taking of my leisure, my time, my effors.</p>

<p><em>Forced labor = slavery</em></p>

<p><em>Violates Principle of Self-Possession</em></p>

<p>To coerce someone to use some person for the sake of the general welfare is wrong, bc it calls to the question of fundumental fact that we own ourselves <strong>self-possession or self ownership</strong>.</p>

<p>Objections to libertarianism:</p>

<ol>
<li>The poor need the money more</li>
<li>Taxation by consent of the governed is not coerced</li>
<li>The successfil owe a debt to society</li>
</ol>


<p>Liberitarians combat the utility idea of using people as means for the collective happiness by saying the way to put a stop to that utilitarian logic of using persons is to resort to the intuitively powerful idea that <em>we are the proprietors of our own person</em>.</p>

<p>Nozick borrows some idea from John Locke where he accounted for the rise of private property from the state of nature by a chain of reasoning very similar to the one that Nozick and the libertarians use. John Locke said private property arises because when we mix our labor with things unowned things we come to acquire a property right in those things.</p>

<hr />

<p><strong>John Locke</strong></p>

<p>There are certain fundamental individual rights include a natural right to life libery and property and he argues that the right to property is not just a creation of goverment or law, <em>the law of property</em> is a natural rightin the sence it is pre-political, it's a right that attaches to individuals as human beings. He says the state of nature is the state of liberty, human beings are free and equal beings, there is no natural hierarchy and yet there's a difference between a state of libery and the state of licence.</p>

<p>Even I'm free, i'm not free to violate the law of nature, take my own life or to sell myself to slavery (You are the creature of God and God has a bigger property right in us).</p>

<blockquote><p>For men, being all the workmanship (мастерство) of one omnipotent (всемогущий), and infinitely wise maker (God), they are his property, whose workmanship they are, made to last during his, not one another's pleasure. John Locke</p>

<p>Freedom can't just be a matter of doing whatever we want. The state of nature has a law of nature to govern it which obliges everyone: and reason, which is that law, teches all mankind, who will but consult it, that being all equal and independent, no one ought to harm another in his life, health, liberty or possession (владение).</p></blockquote>

<p>Natural rights is inalienable (неотъемлемые). <strong>Inalienable</strong> it's not for us to alienate(отчуждать) them or to get them up to give them a way to trade them the way, to sell them.</p>

<p><em>Airlines tickets are inalienable</em>, I own them in the limited sense that I can use them for myself, but I can't trade them away.</p>

<blockquote><p>...every man has a property in his own person. This nobody has any right to but himself. The labor of his body, and the work of his hands, we may say, are properly his. John Locke</p>

<p>Whatsoever then he removes out of the state that nature has provided, and left it in, he has mixed his labor with, and joined to it something that is his own, and thereby makes it his property. John Locke</p>

<p>For this labor being the unqestionable property of the laborer, no man but he can have a right to what that is once joined to, at least where there is enough, and as good left in common for others. John Locke</p>

<p>As much land as a man tills, plants, improves, cultivates and can use the product of, so much is his property. He by his labor does, as it were, enclose it from the common.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h1>Quiz 2 (Justice)</h1>

<ol>
<li>According to Robert Nozick, the state is justified to tax a citizen (even against his or her will) if:</li>
</ol>


<p>The answer is <em>the taxes are used to support nothing more than a minimal state.</em></p>

<ol>
<li>Nozick's Wilt Chamberlain example (or Michael Jordan example) is supposed to illustrate that</li>
</ol>


<p>… liberty upsets patterns and, therefore, patterned conceptions of justice require illegitimate restrictions of liberty.</p>

<ol>
<li>Locke's purpose in examining the "state of nature" is</li>
</ol>


<p>to determine the natural rights of human beings and, thereby, the legitimate extent of political power.</p>

<ol>
<li>According to Locke, is private propert possible in the state of nature?</li>
</ol>


<p>Yes, according to Locke, one can come to own something by mixing one's labor with it and provided there is enough, and as good, left for others.</p>

<ol>
<li>Which of the following best characterizes the difference between Locke and Nozik on the issue of unalienable rights?</li>
</ol>


<p>Nozick thinks that I own myself, and that this means I may do whatever I want with myself - including, for instance, selling myself into slavery. Locke disagrees, he thinks, there are certain rights that I may not alienate, no matter how badly I might want to.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
