<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: humankind | nameless]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/humankind/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-08T14:41:24-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] The discrovery of Ignorance. Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/22/october-22-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/22/october-22-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Until the early modern period humans all over the world invested very little effort in scientific research, because they doubted their ability to obtain new medical or military or economic powers. Kings and emperors certainly gave money to education and scholarship but the main aim of scholarship in the pre-modern world was to preserve existing capabilities and not to acquire new one. The typical king gave money to priests, and philosophers, and poets in the hope that they would legitimize his rule and maintain the social order.</p>

<p>In the last five centuries howevers, humans increasingly came to believe that they could gain new, more and more powers by investing money and resources in scientific research.</p>

<p>Since cognitive revolutions, humans have always tried to figure out how the universe works. Out ancestors, thousands and even ten of thousands of years ago, put great deal of time and effort in trying to discover the rules that govern the natural world around them. So, what is so <em>special and different</em> about <strong>modern science</strong>?</p>

<p>Modern science differs from all previous traditions of knowledge in three critical ways:</p>

<ul>
<li>If differs its willingness to admit ignorance. Modern science is based on the admission that we do not know everything. Even more importantly, modern science accepts that the things that we think we know, could still be proven wrong as we gain more knowledge.</li>
<li>The second unique characteristic is the centrality of observation and mathematics. Gathering observations on the world, and using mathematical tools to connect these observations into comprehensive theories.</li>
<li>The third unique feature of modern science is that it aims to acquire new powers. It uses theories in order to acquire new powers, and in particular in order to develop new technologies. The real aim of modern science is not truth, it is power.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] The Law of Religion. Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/16/october-16-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/16/october-16-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A religion that recognizes the legitimacy of other faith, implies either that its god is not the supreme power of the universe or that it reveived from the one and only god, only part of the universal truth. "If our religion is true no other religion can also simultaneously be true."</p>

<p><strong>Dualistic religions</strong> - are religions that believe in the existence not of one supreme Good but of two opposing powers, good and evil. Dualism believes that evil is an independent power, which is not created by the good god and is not subordinate to it.</p>

<p>Wars, plague, death, suffer - this is God's way of allowing for human free will. If there was no evil in the world, humans could not choose between good and evel; and hence, there would be no free will.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] The Law of Religion. Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/15/october-15-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/15/october-15-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We already read about the role of money and of empires, on this week we will focus on <strong>religion</strong>. Religion can be defined as a system of human laws and values, which is founded on a belief in a super human order. Religion must believe in a super human order which is not the product of human whims, of human agreements.</p>

<p><strong>Animism</strong> is the belief that the world os populated not only by humans but also an abundance of other beings. Each of them having their own personality, needs and desires. Like trees, rocks, fairies, ghosts, demons.</p>

<p><strong>Polytheism</strong> also tends to believe in all these holy rocks and trees with demons and fairies, but it also believes very importantly, in very powerful entities which they call goods. Rain god, sun god, moon god.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday. part 3 [humankind] Imperial Visions. part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/09/october-09-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/09/october-09-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>The urge to rescue the past as something living, instead of using it as the material of progress, has been satisfied only in art, in which even history, as a representation of past life, is included. As long as art does not insist on being treated as knowledge, and thus exclude itself from praxis, it is tolerated by social praxis in the same way as pleasure.</p></blockquote>

<p>Culture can provide us the reminders, pleasurable reminders of alternatives to this totalitarian picture generated by the Enlightenment.</p>

<p>Art too is used by the forces of domination.</p>

<blockquote><p>The regression of the masses today lies in their inability to hear with their own ears what has not already been heard, to touch with their hands what has not previously been grasped; it is the new form of blindness which supersedes that of vanquished myth.</p>

<p>But a true praxis capable of overturning the status quo depends on theory's refusal to yield to the oblivion in which society allows thought to ossify (костенеть).</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Foucault</strong> who was a historian, a philosopher wrote about art and literature, he was an activist, he participated in the French Postmodernism, in fact was a leader of French Postmodernism. He didn't want to find the really real, he didn't want to find a total dialectic. He wanted to do in his work was to tell the story of progress in such a way that we would see how what we thought of was progress was actually a form of greater social control and homogenization (make uniform or similar).</p>

<hr />

<h2>Imperial Visions</h2>

<p>When you look at the world today, how the world today in being run. You see that the world in the early 21st century is not being governed and run by a particular state of government, but by a global caste of business people, engineers, people in the academia, in arts, in the universities and so forth. These people who run the world, they increasingly have the same interests and viewpoint about the world, the same culture.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] From Critical Theory to Postmodernism [humankind] Imperial Visions]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/08/october-08-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/08/october-08-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Human beings purchase the increase in their power with estrangement from that over which it is exerted. Enlightenment stands in the same relationship to things as the dictator to human beings. He knows them to the extent thaat he can manipulate them. Horkheimer and Adorno</p></blockquote>

<p>Knowledge becomes the ability to manipulate things. And that, will eventually sew the seed of our own destruction. They actually see modern technology being used for mass killings, for effectient murderd, for control of people against their interest.</p>

<p>I really can understand, because I can manipulate. It is a big victory of enlightenment. If you can only show you understand something by your power of manipulation understanding is linked to tyranny.</p>

<blockquote><p>Each human being has been endowed with a self of his or her own, different from all others, so that it could all the more surely be made the same. But because that self never quite fitted te mold, enlightenment throughout the liberalistic period has always sympathized with social coercion. The unity of the manipulated collective consists in the negation of each individual and the scorn poured on the type of society which could make people into individuals.</p></blockquote>

<p>Their point is that the persistent pursuit of equality actually creates the grounds for more coercion.</p>

<blockquote><p>The actual is validated, knowledge confines itself to repeating it, thought makes itself mere tautology. The more completely the machinery of thought subjugates existence, the more blindly it is satisfied with reproducing it. Enlightenment thereby regresses to the mythology it has never been able to escape. Michael Foucault</p></blockquote>

<p>Scitistic ways of approaching the world are only validated by mirroring the world as it is. Rather than trying imagining the world as it might be, rather than taking critical perspective on the status quo, the positivists quantitatively orientated an enlightened mode of thinking.</p>

<hr />

<h2>Imperial Visions</h2>

<p>Sapience instinctively divide humanity, divide its own specie into two parts, there is we and they, everybody else.</p>

<p>It's very problematic to argue that empires are purely evil because empires are responsible, not only for the unification of humankind, but also for much of our culture today all around the world. Indeed, the very values that prompt many people to criticize empires, values like himan rights and democracy and self-determination, these very values were spread around the world by the empires, by the European empires.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
