<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: humankind | nameless]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/humankind/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-02T12:01:13-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] The discrovery of Ignorance. Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/22/october-22-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/22/october-22-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Until the early modern period humans all over the world invested very little effort in scientific research, because they doubted their ability to obtain new medical or military or economic powers. Kings and emperors certainly gave money to education and scholarship but the main aim of scholarship in the pre-modern world was to preserve existing capabilities and not to acquire new one. The typical king gave money to priests, and philosophers, and poets in the hope that they would legitimize his rule and maintain the social order.</p>

<p>In the last five centuries howevers, humans increasingly came to believe that they could gain new, more and more powers by investing money and resources in scientific research.</p>

<p>Since cognitive revolutions, humans have always tried to figure out how the universe works. Out ancestors, thousands and even ten of thousands of years ago, put great deal of time and effort in trying to discover the rules that govern the natural world around them. So, what is so <em>special and different</em> about <strong>modern science</strong>?</p>

<p>Modern science differs from all previous traditions of knowledge in three critical ways:</p>

<ul>
<li>If differs its willingness to admit ignorance. Modern science is based on the admission that we do not know everything. Even more importantly, modern science accepts that the things that we think we know, could still be proven wrong as we gain more knowledge.</li>
<li>The second unique characteristic is the centrality of observation and mathematics. Gathering observations on the world, and using mathematical tools to connect these observations into comprehensive theories.</li>
<li>The third unique feature of modern science is that it aims to acquire new powers. It uses theories in order to acquire new powers, and in particular in order to develop new technologies. The real aim of modern science is not truth, it is power.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
