<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[nameless]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-17T18:06:23-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science August 15th, 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/17/science-august-15th/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-17T18:05:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/17/science-august-15th</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Технологии на этой неделе (8 - 15 августа 2014)</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Ученые создали лазер, который может определять взрывчатые вещества и наркотики на             расстоянии одного километра. Технология использует <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D0%BE%D0%BC%D0%B1%D0%B8%D0%BD%D0%B0%D1%86%D0%B8%D0%BE%D0%BD%D0%BD%D0%BE%D0%B5_%D1%80%D0%B0%D1%81%D1%81%D0%B5%D1%8F%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%B5_%D1%81%D0%B2%D0%B5%D1%82%D0%B0">комбинационное рассеяние света</a> (грубо говоря, используется спектроскопия, когда можно видеть изменения частоты излучения)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/8/11/5991259/scientists-made-a-laser-than-can-detect-explosives-from-half-a-mile">Scientists made a laser that can detect explosives from half a mile away</a></p></li>
<li><p>Исследователи разработали временную татуировку способную отслеживать тренировочный          прогресс и одновременно производить из пота достаточно мощности для зарядки небольших        электронных устройств.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2014/08/140813103134.htm">Temporary tattoo biobatteries produce power from sweat </a></p></li>
<li><p>Ученые из Гарварда создали самоорганизующийся рой из 1024 микро-роботов (управляймый       через IR).</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://khakimov.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/xK54Bu9HFRw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>

<p><a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/a-self-organizing-thousand-robot-swarm">A self-organizing thousand-robot swarm</a></p></li>
<li><p>Крупная Южно-Корейская корпорация Daewoo Shipbuilding начало оснащать рабочих одеваемым     экзоскелетами, которые позволят им дополнительно поднимать до 120 кг.</p>

<p><img src="http://static.ddmcdn.com/gif/blogs/dnews-files-2014-08-robotic-exoskeleton-shipbuilding-670-jpg.jpg" alt="exoskeleton" /></p>

<p><a href="http://news.discovery.com/tech/robotics/exoskeleton-suit-workers-don-suit-for-heavy-lifting-140805.htm">Exoskeleton First: Workers Don Suit for Heavy Lifting</a></p></li>
<li><p>Samsung заключил сделку о покупке компании SmartThings (IOT) за 200 миллионов долларов,    раскрыв планы о использовании их открытой платформы, которая уже насчитывает 1000             совместимых устройств, чтобы объеденить и наделить интеллектом все окружающие нас            устройства.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.bwbx.io/cms/2013-02-14/tech_smartthings08__01__630x420.jpg" alt="smart things" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/aarontilley/2014/08/14/samsung-smartthings-acquisition-2/">Samsung Acquires SmartThings, A Fast-Growing Home Automation Startup</a></p></li>
<li><p>Вживленные нервные стволовые клетки (neuronal stem cells, наверное имеется ввиду            стволовая клетка, которая характеризуется своей способностью дифференцироваться в          несколько типов клеток с помощью внешних стимулов из окружащего состояния) успешно           создают нейроны и синапсисы став функциональной частью головного мозга мыши, повышая       надежды на возможность создания способов лечения нейродегенеративных заболеваний, таких   как &#8220;Болезнь Паркинсона&#8221;.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.kurzweilai.net/images/transplanted-neural-cells.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/implanted-neuronal-stem-cells-generate-neurons-and-synapses-becoming-a-functioning-part-of-mouse-brain">Implanted neuronal stem cells generate neurons and synapses, becoming a functioning part of mouse brain</a></p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science August 8th, 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/08/science-august-8th/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-08T14:38:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/08/science-august-8th</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p>Новое исследование показало, что транскраниальная магнитная стимуляция (неинвазивно       стимуляция коры головного мозга при помощи коротких магнитных импульсов) может изменять     организацию мозга, что в свою очередь может помочь в борьбе с депрессией, эпилепсией и       звон в ушах (tinnitus).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2014/08/140806025318.htm">source</a></p></li>
<li><p>Колоссальное исследование показало, что генетически модифицированная мышь с              отсутствующим протеином TRAP-1 проживает дольше и в тоже время наблюдается значительно        уменьшение болезней связанных с возрастом, такие как дегенерация тканей и избыток веса.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/rewired-mice-show-signs-of-longer-lives-with-fewer-age-related-illnesses">source</a></p></li>
<li><p>Инженеры разработали технологию под названием &#8220;Wi-Fi обратного рассеивания&#8221;, которая        используя присутствующие окружающие сигналы как источник энергии для безбатарейных            устройств.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9250171/Researchers_promote_battery_free_Wi_Fi_technology">source</a></p></li>
<li><p>IBM объявило о радикально новой архитектуре чипов, которые могут эмулировать структуры      головного мозга и уже достигли эмуляции 1 миллиона нейронов и более 256 миллионов          программируемых синапсисов.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/ibm-launches-functioning-brain-inspired-chip">source</a></p></li>
<li><p>Исследовадетил из MIT, Adobe и Microsoft смогли реконструировать аудио разговор просто        снимая на видео и анализируя малейшие вибрации на объектах (например снимая на видео         пакет с чипсами находящийся в 5 метрах за звуконепроницаемым стеклом).</p>

<p><a href="http://time.com/3080126/mit-potato-chip-bag-spying/">source</a></p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science August 3, 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/03/science-august-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-03T17:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/03/science-august-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p>Tesla Motors подписала договор с Panasonic о строительстве               гигафабрики стоимость 5 миллиардов долларов, что позволит сократить   стоимость на 30% и производить больше аккамуляторов, чем все            фабрики (производящие литий-ионные аккамуляторы) вместе взятые.</p></li>
<li><p>Исследователи создали наночастицы (диаметр 15 нанометров), которые       могут доставлять лекарство или другие молекулы в заданные живые      клетки.</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://khakimov.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/X5EzUyDrcjo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p></li>
<li><p>Hubble телескоп обнаружил самую отделенную линзированную (lensing?)    галактику. Насколько я понимаю, гравитационной линзой называют            массивные тела или системы тел, искревляющие своим гравитационным      полем направление распространения электромагнитного излучения.             Приблизительный вес в 180 миллиардов раз больше, чем наше солнце.        Свет от новой галактики был в пути 9.6 миллиардов лет, чтобы          достигнуть нашей планеты.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.redorbit.com/media/uploads/2014/08/farthest-cosmic-lens-617x416.jpg" alt="" /></p></li>
<li><p>Вакцина против малярии предохраняет детей от заражения на 18 месяцев   . Еще один шаг ближе к борьбе с малярией у детей в Африке, но             вопрос о цене остается открытым.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.techtimes.com/articles/11632/20140801/malaria-vaccine-rts-s-as01-protects-children-for-18-months-when-will-it-be-ready.htm"></a></p></li>
<li><p>Инженеры разработали прототип таблеточного экрана, который              компенсирует проблемы со зрением за счет добавления тонкого             микроточечного фильтра повышающий резкость изображения.</p>

<p><img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/76625000/jpg/_76625878_eyeglassdisplay-macaroons670.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-28562432"></a></p></li>
<li><p>Новый источник стволовых клеток обнаружен в зубах.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.kinja-img.com/gawker-media/image/upload/s--tRUdUMlV--/c_fit,fl_progressive,q_80,w_636/aawpvrec67dbip89h7yo.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://gizmodo.com/there-are-cells-inside-teeth-that-can-turn-back-into-st-1614066776"></a></p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science July 27, 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/07/30/science-july-27/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T22:27:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/07/30/science-july-27</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p>Ученые впервые смогли удалить ВИЧ вирус из ДНК человека. Результат обнадеживающий для одной       клетки, но вопрос о миллионах других зараженных остается открытым, как выбрать и излечить            остальные все (100%) зараженные, чтобы вирус остановился и не продолжал копировать себя?</p>

<p><img src="http://images.gizmag.com/hero/hiv-virus-cu.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.the-scientist.com/?articles.view/articleNo/40531/title/Genome-Editing-Cuts-Out-HIV/">Genome Editing Cuts Out HIV</a></p></li>
<li><p>Найденные при раскопках в Сибири останки нового вида и рода травоядного динозавра                     &#8220;Кулиндадромеус забайкальский&#8221; указывает на то, что перья, вероятно, существовали у общего           предка всех динозавров.</p>

<p><img src="http://cs619631.vk.me/v619631842/12bf7/9U0CXcHiWnk.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.scientificamerican.com/article/most-dinosaurs-may-have-sported-birdlike-feathers">Most Dinosaurs May Have Sported Birdlike Feathers</a></p></li>
<li><p>Стенфордский биолог предупредил о массов вымирании представителей мегафауны включающих в себя        слонов, носорогов, полярных медведей и бесчисленное множество других видов по всему миру.            Крупные животные, как правило, имеют более низкий темп прироста и производят меньше потомства,       а их размер и количество мяса делает их легкой и более привлекательной добычей для охотников.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.stihi.ru/pics/2012/10/04/5804.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://news.stanford.edu/news/2014/july/sixth-mass-extinction-072414.html">6th mass extinction event</a></p></li>
<li><p>Теоретики предложили анализировать внеземные промышленные загрязнения для поисков внеземной      цивилизаций.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.dvice.com/sites/dvice/files/styles/blog_post_media/public/jellybldgs11.jpg?itok=8Ksh4tuA" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://phys.org/news/2014-07-approach-extraterrestrial-intelligence-alien-polluters.html">Search for extraterrestrial intelligence</a></p></li>
<li><p>Британские ученые научились определять рак через анализ крови.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.doctortipster.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/07/Ovarian-Cancer-Blood-Test.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.telegraph.co.uk/health/10993401/British-scientists-develop-blood-test-that-could-detect-all-forms-of-cancer.html">blood test that could detect all forms of cancer</a></p></li>
<li><p>Исследователи создали первый биологический уселитель, который для уселения биологических             сигналов, использует ДНК и безвредную E.coli (кишечная палочка) бактерию. Возможно использовать  при создании нового типа сенсоров для определения вредных токсинов или заболеваний в организме        до того, как они нанесут вред.</p>

<p><img src="http://newscenter.lbl.gov/wp-content/uploads/sites/2/2011/11/E.coli-Th1.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www3.imperial.ac.uk/newsandeventspggrp/imperialcollege/newssummary/news_24-7-2014-17-21-47">First ever biological amplifier created by Imperial scientists</a></p>

<p><a href="http://nar.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2014/07/15/nar.gku593">Study</a></p></li>
<li><p>Только 8.2 процента человеческого генома несет в себе функционально значение, остальное, по      заявлению ученых из Оксфордского университета, является пережитками эволюции или вообще не           несет никаких функций.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.nationalgeographic.com/wpf/media-live/photos/000/178/cache/human-genome-ten-years-in_17889_600x450.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.redorbit.com/news/health/1113198987/human-genome-functionality-study-072514/">Less Than 10 Percent Of Human DNA Actually Has A Function</a></p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Шаги прогресса (19 Июля - 26 Июля)]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/07/28/tech-19-26-july-2014/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-28T22:39:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/07/28/tech-19-26-july-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p>SpaceX совершил успешную посадку первой ступени Falcon 9, тем самым подтвердив возвожность             последовательного вхождения из космоса на гиперзвуковой скорости, перезапуск главных двигателей    и плавной посадки на минимальной скорости.</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://khakimov.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/CQnR5fhCXkQ" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p></li>
<li><p>Новый прорыв с лазером получающийся при использовании одного искусственного атома для                генерирации и излучения частицы света, играющий важную роль в создании квантовых компьютеров,       который будут превосходить текущие суперкомпьютеры. Свет от лазера получают путем пропускания         электричества через искусственный атом (искусственный атом состоит из наноразмерных частей          сверхпроводника). Причина использования искусственного атома заключается в том, что теперь это         может быть частью электрической цепи на чипе, чего нельзя сделать с настоящим атомом. С этим        лазером электрическая энергия преобразуется в свет, что дает возможность передавать информацию       в/из квантового компьютера.</p>

<p><a href="http://now.dartmouth.edu/2014/07/dancing-electrons-are-at-the-heart-of-a-laser-breakthrough/">News</a></p></li>
<li><p>Kickstarter кампания от Cyberith Virtualizer позволяет пользователям свободно двигаться в виртуальном мире используя всенаправленную беговую дорожку (через оптические сенсоры на поверхности дорожки определяет каждое движение ног, а сенсоры в опорах позволяют определять вертикальное положение).</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://khakimov.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/fbu8OUq1CUE" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p></li>
<li><p>Ученым удалось преобразовать разряженный воздух в &#8216;оптоволокно&#8217;, которое может передавать и усиливать световые сигналы без каких-либо кабелей.</p>

<p><img src="http://static.ddmcdn.com/gif/zap-it-with-lasers-opener-670.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://news.discovery.com/tech/gear-and-gadgets/optical-fiber-made-out-of-thin-air-140723.htm">News</a></p></li>
<li><p>Исследователи разработали устройство позволяющее определять изменения указывающие на болезнь Альцгеймера за 15-20 лет до клинического диагноза. Прибор позволяет смотреть через сетчатку глаза (идентично тому, как это делают офтальмологи) и видеть изменения, которые позволяют диагностировать заболевание.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.eurekalert.org/pub_releases/2014-07/cmc-son070814.php">News</a></p></li>
<li><p>Исследователи из MIT показали процесс который используя влажность в воздухе может генерировать достаточно электричества для зарядки мобильного телефона или очистки воды.</p>

<p><img src="http://wp.streetwise.co/wp-content/uploads//2014/07/Electric-Humidity.gif" alt="" /></p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Consciousness as a Problem in Philosophy and Neurobiology]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/07/15/consciousness-as-a-problem-in-philosophy-and-neurobiology/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-15T17:34:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/07/15/consciousness-as-a-problem-in-philosophy-and-neurobiology</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Searle">Professor John Searle</a> about consciousness.</p>

<iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://khakimov.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/6nTQnvGxEXw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] The discrovery of Ignorance. Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/22/october-22-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/22/october-22-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Until the early modern period humans all over the world invested very little effort in scientific research, because they doubted their ability to obtain new medical or military or economic powers. Kings and emperors certainly gave money to education and scholarship but the main aim of scholarship in the pre-modern world was to preserve existing capabilities and not to acquire new one. The typical king gave money to priests, and philosophers, and poets in the hope that they would legitimize his rule and maintain the social order.</p>

<p>In the last five centuries howevers, humans increasingly came to believe that they could gain new, more and more powers by investing money and resources in scientific research.</p>

<p>Since cognitive revolutions, humans have always tried to figure out how the universe works. Out ancestors, thousands and even ten of thousands of years ago, put great deal of time and effort in trying to discover the rules that govern the natural world around them. So, what is so <em>special and different</em> about <strong>modern science</strong>?</p>

<p>Modern science differs from all previous traditions of knowledge in three critical ways:</p>

<ul>
<li>If differs its willingness to admit ignorance. Modern science is based on the admission that we do not know everything. Even more importantly, modern science accepts that the things that we think we know, could still be proven wrong as we gain more knowledge.</li>
<li>The second unique characteristic is the centrality of observation and mathematics. Gathering observations on the world, and using mathematical tools to connect these observations into comprehensive theories.</li>
<li>The third unique feature of modern science is that it aims to acquire new powers. It uses theories in order to acquire new powers, and in particular in order to develop new technologies. The real aim of modern science is not truth, it is power.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] Postmodern Identities. Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/21/october-21-monday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/21/october-21-monday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Judith Butler and Slavoj Zizek, who are both very active and in some respects in the prime of their careers. Judith Butler started her carier with the work on French Hegelianism and her dissertation had to do with the status of Hegel in modern France. She moved on to work on gender and sexuality in a book called <strong>Gender Trouble</strong> which really was a game changer in the field of women&#8217;s studie gay and lesbian studies and queer studie as it came to be called later.</p>

<blockquote><p>To understand gender as a historical category, however, is to accept that gender, understood as one way of culturally configuring a body, is open to a continual remaking, and that &#8216;anatomy&#8217; and &#8216;sex&#8217; are not without cultural framing. <strong>Undoing Gender</strong></p>

<p>If gender is a kind of doing, an incessant activity performed, in part, without one&#8217;s knowing and without one&#8217;s willing, it is not for that reason automatic or mechanical. On the contrary, it is a practice of improvisation within a scene of constraint.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>[Humankind] The Law of Religion. Part 4</h2>

<p>Humanism is the belief that Homo sapiens has an unique and sacred nature which is fundamentally different from the nature of all the other animals and of all other phenomena in the universe. Humanists believe that the unique nature of Homo sapiense is the most important thing in the world and it is this that determines the meaning of everything that happens in the universe.</p>

<p><strong>Liberal Humanism</strong> which believes that humanity is a quality of individual humans. According to Liberals, the sacred nature of humanity resides within each and every individual Homo sapiens. And therefore, the supreme values of the world is the liberty of individuals.</p>

<p><strong>Socialist Humanism</strong> believes that humanity is collective and not individualistic. Socialists hold as sacred not the inner voice of each individual, but the species Homo sapiens as a whole, seeks equality between all humans. Inequality is the worst blasphemy (богохульство) against the sanctity of humanity, because inequality privileges peripheral qualities of humans over their common universal essence. For example, when the rich are given privileges which are withheld from the poor, it means that we value money more than we value the universal essence of all humans which is similar for everybody, for rich and poor alike.</p>

<p><strong>Evolutionary humanism</strong> (the most famous representatives were the Nazis). Nazis too believed in the sanctity of humanity. They had a different defenition of humanity than the Liberals and the Socialists. The Nazis were deeply influenced by the theory of evolution, believed that humankind is not something universal and eternal and unchanging. Rather, they believed that it is a specie of animals which can evolve or degenerate in accordance with the theory of evolution. The main ambition of the Nazis was to protect human kind from the generation extinction and encourage the evolution of human kind into super men.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] The Law of Religion. Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/16/october-16-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/16/october-16-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A religion that recognizes the legitimacy of other faith, implies either that its god is not the supreme power of the universe or that it reveived from the one and only god, only part of the universal truth. &#8220;If our religion is true no other religion can also simultaneously be true.&#8221;</p>

<p><strong>Dualistic religions</strong> - are religions that believe in the existence not of one supreme Good but of two opposing powers, good and evil. Dualism believes that evil is an independent power, which is not created by the good god and is not subordinate to it.</p>

<p>Wars, plague, death, suffer - this is God&#8217;s way of allowing for human free will. If there was no evil in the world, humans could not choose between good and evel; and hence, there would be no free will.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] The Law of Religion. Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/15/october-15-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/15/october-15-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We already read about the role of money and of empires, on this week we will focus on <strong>religion</strong>. Religion can be defined as a system of human laws and values, which is founded on a belief in a super human order. Religion must believe in a super human order which is not the product of human whims, of human agreements.</p>

<p><strong>Animism</strong> is the belief that the world os populated not only by humans but also an abundance of other beings. Each of them having their own personality, needs and desires. Like trees, rocks, fairies, ghosts, demons.</p>

<p><strong>Polytheism</strong> also tends to believe in all these holy rocks and trees with demons and fairies, but it also believes very importantly, in very powerful entities which they call goods. Rain god, sun god, moon god.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/10/october-10-thursday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/10/october-10-thursday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>When people think they&#8217;re pursuing sexual freedom, they create new categories for how you should pursue sexual freedom. New forms of identity to which you should conform even if that identity is liberatory, is outside of the main stream. But you create a new mode of being that you then have to conform to. This is Foucault&#8217;s great subject. <strong>How we, in a way, police ourselves.</strong> How we dominate ourselves by saying, oh, I am going to be a radical. And now, I have to act like the radicals act.</p>

<p>In other words, you conform to the image of radicalization. Some might you say, well, I am not a diseased person because I like to have sex with people of my own gender. No, no, I am not that, I am free, I am gay, or I&#8217;m a homosexual or I&#8217;m a lesbian. I am free. And <strong>Foucault</strong> says, yeah, you&#8217;re free, but now notice how we start to have to conform to being gay, being lesbian.</p>

<p>Why do we need always to find a new mode of conformity? A label for our freedom that comes then to repress us.</p>

<blockquote><p>Modern man, for Baudelaire, is not the man who goes off to discover himself, his secrets and his hidden truth; he is the man who tries to invent himself. This modernity does not &#8220;liberate man in his own being&#8221;; it compels him to face the task of producing himself.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday. part 3 [humankind] Imperial Visions. part 3]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/09/october-09-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-09T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/09/october-09-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>The urge to rescue the past as something living, instead of using it as the material of progress, has been satisfied only in art, in which even history, as a representation of past life, is included. As long as art does not insist on being treated as knowledge, and thus exclude itself from praxis, it is tolerated by social praxis in the same way as pleasure.</p></blockquote>

<p>Culture can provide us the reminders, pleasurable reminders of alternatives to this totalitarian picture generated by the Enlightenment.</p>

<p>Art too is used by the forces of domination.</p>

<blockquote><p>The regression of the masses today lies in their inability to hear with their own ears what has not already been heard, to touch with their hands what has not previously been grasped; it is the new form of blindness which supersedes that of vanquished myth.</p>

<p>But a true praxis capable of overturning the status quo depends on theory&#8217;s refusal to yield to the oblivion in which society allows thought to ossify (костенеть).</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Foucault</strong> who was a historian, a philosopher wrote about art and literature, he was an activist, he participated in the French Postmodernism, in fact was a leader of French Postmodernism. He didn&#8217;t want to find the really real, he didn&#8217;t want to find a total dialectic. He wanted to do in his work was to tell the story of progress in such a way that we would see how what we thought of was progress was actually a form of greater social control and homogenization (make uniform or similar).</p>

<hr />

<h2>Imperial Visions</h2>

<p>When you look at the world today, how the world today in being run. You see that the world in the early 21st century is not being governed and run by a particular state of government, but by a global caste of business people, engineers, people in the academia, in arts, in the universities and so forth. These people who run the world, they increasingly have the same interests and viewpoint about the world, the same culture.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] From Critical Theory to Postmodernism [humankind] Imperial Visions]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/08/october-08-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/08/october-08-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>Human beings purchase the increase in their power with estrangement from that over which it is exerted. Enlightenment stands in the same relationship to things as the dictator to human beings. He knows them to the extent thaat he can manipulate them. Horkheimer and Adorno</p></blockquote>

<p>Knowledge becomes the ability to manipulate things. And that, will eventually sew the seed of our own destruction. They actually see modern technology being used for mass killings, for effectient murderd, for control of people against their interest.</p>

<p>I really can understand, because I can manipulate. It is a big victory of enlightenment. If you can only show you understand something by your power of manipulation understanding is linked to tyranny.</p>

<blockquote><p>Each human being has been endowed with a self of his or her own, different from all others, so that it could all the more surely be made the same. But because that self never quite fitted te mold, enlightenment throughout the liberalistic period has always sympathized with social coercion. The unity of the manipulated collective consists in the negation of each individual and the scorn poured on the type of society which could make people into individuals.</p></blockquote>

<p>Their point is that the persistent pursuit of equality actually creates the grounds for more coercion.</p>

<blockquote><p>The actual is validated, knowledge confines itself to repeating it, thought makes itself mere tautology. The more completely the machinery of thought subjugates existence, the more blindly it is satisfied with reproducing it. Enlightenment thereby regresses to the mythology it has never been able to escape. Michael Foucault</p></blockquote>

<p>Scitistic ways of approaching the world are only validated by mirroring the world as it is. Rather than trying imagining the world as it might be, rather than taking critical perspective on the status quo, the positivists quantitatively orientated an enlightened mode of thinking.</p>

<hr />

<h2>Imperial Visions</h2>

<p>Sapience instinctively divide humanity, divide its own specie into two parts, there is we and they, everybody else.</p>

<p>It&#8217;s very problematic to argue that empires are purely evil because empires are responsible, not only for the unification of humankind, but also for much of our culture today all around the world. Indeed, the very values that prompt many people to criticize empires, values like himan rights and democracy and self-determination, these very values were spread around the world by the empires, by the European empires.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] From Critical Theory to Postmodernism [humankind] Imperial Visions]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/07/october-07-monday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/07/october-07-monday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Horkheimer and Adorno writing in the Nazi period what problem are they trying to address? What issue are they trying to explain?</p>

<p>They are trying to understand the attractions of fascism and Nazism, why the working classes don&#8217;t rebel against their owners of capital, why they don&#8217;t rebel against the massive corporations or the political parties that feed them.</p>

<p>They saw this really nefarious (гнусный, бесчестный) globalization as a product of enlightenment. They asw modernity and enlughtenment joining hands to create a new universal myth that entrapped us with its appeal while controlling us and diminising our freedom at every step.</p>

<blockquote><p>Englightenment, understood in the widest sense as the advance of thought, has always aimed at liberating human beings from fear and installing them as masters. Yet the wholly enlightened earth is radiant with triumphant calamity. Enlightenment&#8217;s program was the disenchantment of the world. Horkheimer and Adorno</p>

<p>Techonology is the essence of this knowlegde. It aims to produce neither concepts nor images, nor the joy of understanding, but method, exploitation of the labor of others&#8230; What human beings seek to learn from nature is how to use it to dominate wholly both it and human beings. Nothing else counts.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>Imperial Visions</h2>

<p>What empire is? It is a political order which has two very important characteristics:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>rules over a significant number of distinct peoples, each possessing a different cultural identity and a separate territory.</p></li>
<li><p>It has flexible borders and a potentially unlimited appetite.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>It&#8217;s very common today to hear that in the long run, it is not possible to rule effectively over a large number of conquered people, that empires are doomed to failure and to collapse. The second main objection to empires is not only that they don&#8217;t work, but also that they are evil.</p>

<p>Empire has been the world&#8217;s most common form of political organization for the last 2500 years. Emires are a very stable, irrelatively, when compared to other form of goverments, empire is very stable form of government.</p>

<p>Most empires have been collapsed either because of external invasion of external enemies or because of a split within the ruling elite itself.</p>

<p>The standard imperial toolkit with which you build and maintain an empire includes war, enslavement, deportation and genocide.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/03/october-03-thursday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/03/october-03-thursday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By playing with new devices, you understand how to us it.</p>

<blockquote><p>We got to know the nature of calculating by learning to calculate. Ludwig Wittgenstein</p>

<p>A meaning of a word is a kind of employment of it. For it is what we learn when the word is incorporated into our language.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Words get meaning through use.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>Is there a why? Must I now begin to trust somewhere? That is to say: somewhere I must begin with not-doubting&#8230; Wittgenstein</p>

<p>The difficulty is to realize the groundlessness (необоснованность) of our believing.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/02/october-02-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/02/october-02-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Even while we celebrate individualism, we have this tendency to create a situation where individualism results in everybody trying to be an individual in the same way. It creates even more conditions for conformity. <em>Emerson is the enemy of conformity, he is the enemy of imitation.</em></p>

<blockquote><p>Insist on yourself; never imitate.</p></blockquote>

<p>Finding yourself throught action rather than thought a process that aims to discover a foundation or some goal for you entire life. <strong>You are free to recreate every day.</strong> In fact by recreating yourself every day you have this opennes to experience of that can be extraordinarily powerful and conform to no onse else at all.</p>

<h2>Ludwig Wittgenstein</h2>

<p>How language really works when someone&#8217;s asking for objects in a contruction project and also how we learn languages, how to understand the ways in which our words get meaning.</p>

<blockquote><p>From its seeming to me - or to everyone - to be so, it doesn&#8217;t follow that it is so. What we can ask is whether it can make sense to doubt it. Ludwig Wittgenstein</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>[humankind] The Direction of History</h2>

<p>People do their work or exchange their goods to money when they trust the figments of the collective imagination. <strong>Trust</strong> is the real raw material from which all types of money in history have been minted.</p>

<p>Money is the most universal and most effictien system of mutual trust ever devised by human beings. How to create trust in money?</p>

<p>The first coins in history, as far as we know, were struck around 640 BC by Kind Elliotus of the kingdom of Lydia (western Turkey).</p>

<p>Religion wants us to believe in something like in God, money doesn&#8217;t ask us to believe in anything in particular. Money simply asks us to believe that other people believe in something.</p>

<p>Universal principles of money:</p>

<ul>
<li>Universal convertivility</li>
<li>Universal trust</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/01/october-01-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/01/october-01-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.emersoncentral.com/selfreliance.htm">Self-Reliance by Ralph Waldo Emerson</a></p>

<p>We don&#8217;t have to wait for something big to happen in our lives, our everyday lives should enliven, should bring the world to life for ourselves and for those around us.</p>

<blockquote><p>The great gift are not got by analysis. Everything good is on the highway.</p></blockquote>

<p>Don&#8217;t try to analyse whether people are real, whether this experience counts, whether I am authentic, whether I am honest, take to the road, take to life. This notion that <em>everything good is on the highway</em> will inspire American travelers from Woody Guthrie to Jack Kerouac who see that the best thinking is not done behind a desk or in a library, in front of a computer. Everything good is on the highway.</p>

<blockquote><p>Life has no memory. That which proceeds in succession might be remembered, but that which is coexistent, or ejaculated from a deeper cause, as yet far from being conscious knows not its own tendency.</p></blockquote>

<p>Learning from the past is a way of avoiding the present.</p>

<blockquote><p>To believe your own thought, to believe that what is true for you in your private heart is true for all men, - that is genius.</p>

<p>Trust thyself: every heart vibrates to that iron string.</p>

<p>It is easy in the world to live after the world&#8217;s opinion; it is easy in solitude to live after our own; but the great man is he who in the midst of the crowd keeps with perfect sweetness the independence of solitude.</p>

<p>What I must do is all that concerns me, not what the people think. This rule, equally arduous in actual and in intellectual life, may serve for the whole distinction between greatness and meanness. It is the harder, because you will always find those who think they know what is your duty better than you know it. It is easy in the world to live after the world&#8217;s opinion; it is easy in solitude to live after our own; but the great man is he who in the midst of the crowd keeps with perfect sweetness the independence of solitude.</p>

<p>Our housekeeping is mendicant, our arts, our occupations, our marriages, our religion, we have not chosen, but society has chosen for us. We are parlour soldiers. We shun the rugged battle of fate, where strength is born.</p></blockquote>

<p>If you don&#8217;t live ever in a new day, because if you don&#8217;t live that way, if you are encumbered by your memory, if you are encumbered by the crowd, what will happen is that your will over time become conform more and more to someone else&#8217;s way of life. You will conform more and more to either the status quo or the dominant majority or even a aggressive minority, but you will be conforming to someone else&#8217;s mode of life.</p>

<blockquote><p>A foolish consistency is the hobgoblin of little minds, adored by little statesmen and philosophers and divines.</p>

<p>With consistency a great soul has simply nothing to do.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>[Human Kind] The Direction of History</h2>

<p><strong>History of money</strong></p>

<p>Initially human had no money. Each band hunted and gathered and manufactured almost everything it needed (meat, medicine, sandals and so on). Just on the basis of our personal relationship assuming that one day he will be in trouble or he will need something from me then I will repay the favor which I got from him. It can be also done by simple <em>barter</em>.</p>

<p>Some villages began specializing in producing only one kind of product, let&#8217;s say olive oil. This had bigger advantages because every village could concentrate on what was the ideal products given its location and climate and topography. Specialization also create new <strong>problems</strong>.</p>

<p>The main problem when different people specialize in different tasks is how exactly to manage exchange of goods and services between all the different specialists.</p>

<p>Barter can never form the basis for a really complex economy. Even if you manage to calculate and to agree how many apples are worth a pair of shoes, barter is not always possible because afterl all, in order to make a barter deal, each sides have to want what the other has got to offer.</p>

<p>Money was created many times in many places in history. It was a purely psychological revolution, the invention of monuments simply the creation of a new imagined reality, of a new inter-subjective reality that exists only in the shared imagination of many people, because money is not coins and money is not bank notes. Money is anything that people are willing to use, in order to represent the value of other things for the purpose of exchanging goods and services. <strong>The value of money depends only on our imagination.</strong></p>

<p>In 2006, the sum total of money in the world was estimated at about $473 trillion and more than 90% of all the money in the world that appear in our bank account, they exist only on computer screens and servers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/september-30-monday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/september-30-monday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two person who were important for contemporary philosophy Ralph Waldo Emerson and Ludwin Wittgenstein. Emerson is a key figure in American intellectual history, cultural history, but until pretty recently wasn&#8217;t seen as a key figure in philosophy. Often flowery (витиеватый) writer, he is a writer of wonderful sentences one of the most quotable authors in American history. Emerson&#8217;s philosophical contribution to American culture as an author whose importance rivals that of Nietzsche and of Heidegger both of whom were influenced by Emerson.</p>

<p>Emerson was born during the presidency of Thoman Jefferson, so very early in the nineteenth century, lived a long life, he was at some point a minister and left the pulpit, because of a crisis of faith, not so much in the divine being but in instritutionalized religion and became an eassayst and lecturer. Emerson had audiences of thousands of people around the contry who were following his intellectual excursions via lectures in towns across the United States. His departure from enlightenment tradition as it had been imported into the United Stated is really key.</p>

<p><em>The englightenment tradition in the United States was very much indebted to the Lockian Tradition, that is the view that all our ideas come from sensations that we are receptacle of stimuli from the world and that our ideas and then our belief and our work comes as we process the stimulation, the sensation that comes into us. In some ways, thinking of us as a blank slate and having these impressions made upon us by the world.</em> That&#8217;s the tradition that the American progressive thinkes the beginning of the 19th century adopted.</p>

<p>Emerson has a different view, his view is kind of an activist mind, for him, experience isn&#8217;t just receiving the world. Emerson&#8217;s view is that the mind goes out into the world, we make our experience in an active way (something there from Kant). <strong>Experience comes not by just humans being receptacles, but humans creating experience by actively living in the world.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>Grief too will make us idealists. In the death of my son, now more than two years ago, I seem to have lost a beautiful estate, — no more. I cannot get it nearer to me. If tomorrow I should be informed of the bankruptcy of my principal debtors, the loss of my property would be a great inconvenience to me, perhaps, for many years; but it would leave me as it found me, — neither better nor worse. Experience by Ralph Waldo Emerson</p>

<p> Life is a train of moods like a string of beads, and, as we pass through them, they prove to be many-colored lenses which paint the world their own hue, and each shows only what lies in its focus.</p></blockquote>

<p>There are times in our lives when we think that we are living a kind of banal existence. Everything is routine, that you know there, we go to work everyday or we go to school everyday, we have our meals at the same time, we see the same members of our family, our friends, our spouses, our lovers, whatever we&#8217;re depending on our situation. And after while we&#8217;ve realized we&#8217;re not feeling things. It&#8217;s just going thorought life, going through the motions we might say. <strong>And sometimes we want a crisis, you want something big to happen, even if it&#8217;s a bad thing, because it makes feel more alive, more vital.</strong></p>

<p>If you had some crisis, if you had a grief, you would at least wake up to the world, because you&#8217;re living in the world without waking up to it. But grief will make us idealists. There are times when we think that we are away from the world and we hope that some huge even happens, even a horrible event, that will make us at least, feel the world.</p>

<p>But in fact, <strong>it&#8217;s a mistate to think you need some huge experience, some trauma, to wake you up to the world.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>We animate what we can, and we see only what we animate.</p></blockquote>

<p>We make the world alive to us. We enliven the world.</p>

<hr />

<h2>[Human Kind] The Direction of History</h2>

<p>The interaction between different societies tooks all kind of forms, there were of course wars, trades, immigration from one society to the other, religion missionaries coming from one place to another.</p>

<p><strong>Does human history has a clear direction?</strong></p>

<p>All wars, trades, immigrations in history have a clear general direction and this direction is global unity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] Intensity and the Ordinary [humankind] There is No Justice in History]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/27/september-27-friday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/27/september-27-friday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>It was a splendid mind. For if thought is like the keyboard of a piano, divided into so many notes, or like the alphabet is ranged in twenty-six letters all in order, then his splendid mind had one by one, firmly and accurately, until it had reached, say, the letter Q. He reached Q. Very few people in the whole of England ever reach Q&#8230; But after Q? What comes next?</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Web of love</strong> connects one with the other, not a logical deduction, but an intimacy born of affection and art.</p>

<blockquote><p>What is the meaning of life? That was all - a simple question; one that tended to close in on one with years. The great revelation had never come. The great revelation perhaps never did come. Instead there were little daily miracles, illuminations, matches struck unexpectedly in the dark; here was one.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>There is No Justice in History. Part 4</h2>

<p>The most common theory, which tries to explain the patriarchal system, points out that men are physically stronger than women and that men have used the greater physical force, physical power to force women into submission. That means men could monopolize certain economic tasks that demand hard manual labor, like plowing the fields and harvesting wheat or rice or whatever it is. And this gave men <strong>control of food production</strong> and gave them control of the economy which in turned translated into political power.</p>

<p>Problems of this theory: First of all the statement that men are stronger than women is true only on average and also it is true only with regard to certain types of strngths. Secondly, and more importantly, there simple is no direct relation between physical strength and social power smong homo sapiens, among humans.</p>

<p>Another theory explains that the dominance of men over women results not just from strength, but from something which is more complacted, <strong>from aggression</strong>. According to this theory, for millions of years of evolution, men have been evloving to become willing to engage in physical violence much more than women, and this is why throughout history warfare was a monopoly of mainly of men. Men -> war -> control civil society</p>

<p>Now recent studies indeed indicate that the hormonal and cognitive systems of men and women are somewhat different and that men, by nature, becuse of that more violent, more willing to use physical violence against others and therefore men are really better suited to serve as common soldiers than women.</p>

<p>The third most common theory for the rise of patriacrchal societies explain that through millions of years of evolution men and women evolved different survival and reproduction strategies. Men, competed with one another, for access to fetile women, for the opportunity to impregnate the women; therefore, if you wre a man your chance of reproducing and passing your genes to the next generation, depended above all on your ability to defeat other men, and to outperfom other men. A women on the other hand had no problem finding a man that was willing to impregnate her. However if the woman wanted her children to provide her with grandchildren she needed to carry them in her womb for nine long months and then nurture them and take care of them for years because it was not enought just to be impregnated. During all that time of pregnancy and child care woman had fewer opportunities to obtain food and woman reguired a lot of help. In order to ensure the survival of yourself and your children woman need a man.</p>

<p>According to this theory, as time went by, the feminine genes that made it to the next generation therefore belonged to the woman who were the most submissive caretakes, who agreed to everything the man wanted and who spent most of the time just taking care of the children. <em>The result of these different survival strategies according to the theory is that men have been programmed by millions of years of evolution to be ambitious and competitive and to excel in politics and business and so forth.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] Intensity and the Ordinary [humankind] There is No Justice in History]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/26/september-26-thursday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/26/september-26-thursday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Incapacity for belief. Critical thinking as being so important, how teaching people how to be critical and so that they actually will never fall for something that somebody else is selling them in less than sound way. But what happenes is you&#8217;re so good at being ironic and critical or distant is you never have the capacity to like anything or to have strong affection for things because strong affection is usually not based in reason.</p>

<hr />

<h2>There is No Justice in History</h2>

<p>The Bible says in Deuteronomy chapter 22, verses 28 to 29:</p>

<blockquote><p>If a man meets a virgin who is not betrothed to anybody and seizes her and lies with her and they are found then the man who lay with her shall give to the father of the young women 50 sheckels.</p></blockquote>

<p>Child bearing, for example. has been considered woman&#8217;s job in all human societies in history, for the simple reason that men don&#8217;t have wombs. However, around this kind of hard kernel of universal biological differences between men and women, every society that we know of in history, managed to accumulate many cultural ideas and norms that have very little to do with biology. Societies associate a host of qualities and tasks and duties with masculinity (мужественность) and with femininity.</p>

<p>Chimpanzees use sex in order to cement political alliances, establish intimacy and diffuse tensions between individuals in the band and that doesn&#8217;t result in the birth of little chimpanzees.</p>

<p><strong>Masculinuty</strong> - what you need to do, how you need to behave and talk and walk and dress in order to be a man. And this changes a lot from one culture to the other culture.</p>

<p>Males spend much of their lives engaged in all kinds of dramas and conflicts and competitions, just in order to prove that they are real man. And success is not guaranteed. Both females and males may fail to win a claim as real men and real women. Throughout the all of human history males have been willing to risk and even to sacrifice their lives, just so that people would say about them he is a real man.</p>

<p>No matter how a society define what it is to be a real man, and what is it to be a woman, to be a man was always better. This is what scholars mean when they speak about patriarchal societies and patriarchy.</p>

<p><strong>A patriarchai society</strong> is a society that values what is sees as masculine qualities more than it values what is considers to be feminine qualities. They educate males to be men; to think and act in a masculine way. But women, of course, they are still supposed to think and act and dress in a feminine way, and anyone who tries to change it will be punished. But patriarchai society doesn&#8217;t reward men and women equaly. It rewards successful men with much more power and many more privileges than it rewards successful women.</p>

<p>With very few exceptions all known human societies in history, at least since agricultural evolution, were patriarchai societies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
