<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: hack | curious and driven]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/hack/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-10T09:47:06-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Behind the hacks]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/10/25/behind-the-hacks/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-25T18:05:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/10/25/behind-the-hacks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've realized what I have bunch of emails where I've send people "bugs" on their websites (I'll share here only that already fixed "bugs"). As example, once I've read about startup http://1.ai on HN. I thought such a nice domain name and interesting .ai zone =) Couple checks and pretty annoy xss:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Hey guys,</p></p><p><p>Read about you on HN, first of all thanks for the great job and don't<br/>forget to close xss here<br/>http://1.ai/%3Cimg%20src=%22http://i.imgur.com/aAJSR.jpg%22%3E</p></p><p><p>thanks</p></p><p><p>-rus</p></blockquote></p>

<p>just after that i've got email:</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Hello Ruslan,<br/>thank you for your help - will notify the sysadmin asap :)<br/>Enjoy the account and feel free to let me know if you do have suggestions/security ideas.<br/>At the moment beside relatively small things the permissions and security should guarantee that<br/>everything runs smoothly but we will certainly do more fixes (like this one) over time !<br/>best Regards<br/>David</p></blockquote></p>

<p>That's cool when people response very fast and with positive feedback, usually people just ignore emails like this, I have no idea why. Maybe because it seems strange, maybe they don't care about that till time when somebody use it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekends project: Quadrocopter v1.0]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/10/02/weekends-project-quadrocopter-v1-dot-0/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-02T12:03:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/10/02/weekends-project-quadrocopter-v1-dot-0</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Was an interesting quest to build this thing. At the end I've almost gave up about even test drive it and couple weeks it just waited till my friend asked to try outside, because I've tried to test it at home and it wasn't good idea (no pilot expirience, didn't know how to controls work and tried to start with perfect vertical lift-off and of course it didn't work and I thought something wrong with my hands/software/engines/controllers). <em>An old story, we are afraid to fail at something, so it was really easy to give up than just once test it outside.</em></p>

<p>Anyway, I did it and it flies perfectly. Time to improve pilot/control skills and later will upgrade it with camera and maybe with 3d glasses.</p>

<iframe width="640" height="360" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/1ws0lYtuihc?rel=0" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
