<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: quora | curious and driven]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/quora/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-07-15T17:37:59-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Quora Digest 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/08/15/quora-digest-2/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-15T11:10:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/08/15/quora-digest-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><a href="http://www.quora.com/Lifestyle/What-are-some-ways-to-live-a-simple-lifestyle">What are some ways to live a simple lifestyle?</a> All this being said, enjoy yourself. Live simply to allow yourself more time and energy to actually go out and do things, to read things, to learn things, to make things, to spend time with people, to exercise, to travel.</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Money CAN buy happiness]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/08/13/money-can-buy-happiness/"/>
    <updated>2012-08-13T16:05:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/08/13/money-can-buy-happiness</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p><a href="http://www.quora.com/Life-Lessons/What-life-lessons-are-counter-intuitive-or-go-against-common-sense-or-wisdom">What life lessons are counter-intuitive or go against common sense or wisdom?</a> Focus on spending this money in ways that improve your happiness and reduce your stress levels, and be cautious about using it to buy things that other people say you "should" buy.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.quora.com/Life-Advice/How-do-I-stop-myself-feeling-low-when-I-think-of-people-who-have-achieved-so-much-in-life">How do I stop myself feeling low when I think of people who have achieved so much in life?</a> You stop feeling low, by stop waiting. History is full of people who did remarkable things at every age. Become yourself.</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.quora.com/What-was-the-turning-point-in-the-lives-of-various-Quora-users-and-how-has-it-turned-them-into-the-person-they-are-today">What was the turning point in the lives of various Quora users, and how has it turned them into the person they are today?</a> Brian Fey and his story is amazing, read it!</p></li>
<li><p><a href="http://www.quora.com/What-are-some-of-the-best-quotes-about-how-to-live-your-life">What are some of the best quotes about how to live your life?</a></p></li>
</ol>


<blockquote><p>It is not the critic who counts; not the man who points out how the strong man stumbles, or where the doer of deeds could have done them better. The credit belongs to the man who is actually in the arena, whose face is marred by dust and sweat and blood; who strives valiantly; who errs, who comes short again and again, because there is no effort without error and shortcoming; but who does actually strive to do the deeds; who knows great enthusiasms, the great devotions; who spends himself in a worthy cause; who at the best knows in the end the triumph of high achievement, and who at the worst, if he fails, at least fails while daring greatly, so that his place shall never be with those cold and timid souls who neither know victory nor defeat.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
