<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: knowledge | curious and driven]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/knowledge/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-02T19:58:25-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/02/october-02-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/02/october-02-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Even while we celebrate individualism, we have this tendency to create a situation where individualism results in everybody trying to be an individual in the same way. It creates even more conditions for conformity. <em>Emerson is the enemy of conformity, he is the enemy of imitation.</em></p>

<blockquote><p>Insist on yourself; never imitate.</p></blockquote>

<p>Finding yourself throught action rather than thought a process that aims to discover a foundation or some goal for you entire life. <strong>You are free to recreate every day.</strong> In fact by recreating yourself every day you have this opennes to experience of that can be extraordinarily powerful and conform to no onse else at all.</p>

<h2>Ludwig Wittgenstein</h2>

<p>How language really works when someone's asking for objects in a contruction project and also how we learn languages, how to understand the ways in which our words get meaning.</p>

<blockquote><p>From its seeming to me - or to everyone - to be so, it doesn't follow that it is so. What we can ask is whether it can make sense to doubt it. Ludwig Wittgenstein</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>[humankind] The Direction of History</h2>

<p>People do their work or exchange their goods to money when they trust the figments of the collective imagination. <strong>Trust</strong> is the real raw material from which all types of money in history have been minted.</p>

<p>Money is the most universal and most effictien system of mutual trust ever devised by human beings. How to create trust in money?</p>

<p>The first coins in history, as far as we know, were struck around 640 BC by Kind Elliotus of the kingdom of Lydia (western Turkey).</p>

<p>Religion wants us to believe in something like in God, money doesn't ask us to believe in anything in particular. Money simply asks us to believe that other people believe in something.</p>

<p>Universal principles of money:</p>

<ul>
<li>Universal convertivility</li>
<li>Universal trust</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/01/october-01-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/01/october-01-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.emersoncentral.com/selfreliance.htm">Self-Reliance by Ralph Waldo Emerson</a></p>

<p>We don't have to wait for something big to happen in our lives, our everyday lives should enliven, should bring the world to life for ourselves and for those around us.</p>

<blockquote><p>The great gift are not got by analysis. Everything good is on the highway.</p></blockquote>

<p>Don't try to analyse whether people are real, whether this experience counts, whether I am authentic, whether I am honest, take to the road, take to life. This notion that <em>everything good is on the highway</em> will inspire American travelers from Woody Guthrie to Jack Kerouac who see that the best thinking is not done behind a desk or in a library, in front of a computer. Everything good is on the highway.</p>

<blockquote><p>Life has no memory. That which proceeds in succession might be remembered, but that which is coexistent, or ejaculated from a deeper cause, as yet far from being conscious knows not its own tendency.</p></blockquote>

<p>Learning from the past is a way of avoiding the present.</p>

<blockquote><p>To believe your own thought, to believe that what is true for you in your private heart is true for all men, - that is genius.</p>

<p>Trust thyself: every heart vibrates to that iron string.</p>

<p>It is easy in the world to live after the world's opinion; it is easy in solitude to live after our own; but the great man is he who in the midst of the crowd keeps with perfect sweetness the independence of solitude.</p>

<p>What I must do is all that concerns me, not what the people think. This rule, equally arduous in actual and in intellectual life, may serve for the whole distinction between greatness and meanness. It is the harder, because you will always find those who think they know what is your duty better than you know it. It is easy in the world to live after the world's opinion; it is easy in solitude to live after our own; but the great man is he who in the midst of the crowd keeps with perfect sweetness the independence of solitude.</p>

<p>Our housekeeping is mendicant, our arts, our occupations, our marriages, our religion, we have not chosen, but society has chosen for us. We are parlour soldiers. We shun the rugged battle of fate, where strength is born.</p></blockquote>

<p>If you don't live ever in a new day, because if you don't live that way, if you are encumbered by your memory, if you are encumbered by the crowd, what will happen is that your will over time become conform more and more to someone else's way of life. You will conform more and more to either the status quo or the dominant majority or even a aggressive minority, but you will be conforming to someone else's mode of life.</p>

<blockquote><p>A foolish consistency is the hobgoblin of little minds, adored by little statesmen and philosophers and divines.</p>

<p>With consistency a great soul has simply nothing to do.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>[Human Kind] The Direction of History</h2>

<p><strong>History of money</strong></p>

<p>Initially human had no money. Each band hunted and gathered and manufactured almost everything it needed (meat, medicine, sandals and so on). Just on the basis of our personal relationship assuming that one day he will be in trouble or he will need something from me then I will repay the favor which I got from him. It can be also done by simple <em>barter</em>.</p>

<p>Some villages began specializing in producing only one kind of product, let's say olive oil. This had bigger advantages because every village could concentrate on what was the ideal products given its location and climate and topography. Specialization also create new <strong>problems</strong>.</p>

<p>The main problem when different people specialize in different tasks is how exactly to manage exchange of goods and services between all the different specialists.</p>

<p>Barter can never form the basis for a really complex economy. Even if you manage to calculate and to agree how many apples are worth a pair of shoes, barter is not always possible because afterl all, in order to make a barter deal, each sides have to want what the other has got to offer.</p>

<p>Money was created many times in many places in history. It was a purely psychological revolution, the invention of monuments simply the creation of a new imagined reality, of a new inter-subjective reality that exists only in the shared imagination of many people, because money is not coins and money is not bank notes. Money is anything that people are willing to use, in order to represent the value of other things for the purpose of exchanging goods and services. <strong>The value of money depends only on our imagination.</strong></p>

<p>In 2006, the sum total of money in the world was estimated at about $473 trillion and more than 90% of all the money in the world that appear in our bank account, they exist only on computer screens and servers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/september-30-monday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/september-30-monday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two person who were important for contemporary philosophy Ralph Waldo Emerson and Ludwin Wittgenstein. Emerson is a key figure in American intellectual history, cultural history, but until pretty recently wasn't seen as a key figure in philosophy. Often flowery (витиеватый) writer, he is a writer of wonderful sentences one of the most quotable authors in American history. Emerson's philosophical contribution to American culture as an author whose importance rivals that of Nietzsche and of Heidegger both of whom were influenced by Emerson.</p>

<p>Emerson was born during the presidency of Thoman Jefferson, so very early in the nineteenth century, lived a long life, he was at some point a minister and left the pulpit, because of a crisis of faith, not so much in the divine being but in instritutionalized religion and became an eassayst and lecturer. Emerson had audiences of thousands of people around the contry who were following his intellectual excursions via lectures in towns across the United States. His departure from enlightenment tradition as it had been imported into the United Stated is really key.</p>

<p><em>The englightenment tradition in the United States was very much indebted to the Lockian Tradition, that is the view that all our ideas come from sensations that we are receptacle of stimuli from the world and that our ideas and then our belief and our work comes as we process the stimulation, the sensation that comes into us. In some ways, thinking of us as a blank slate and having these impressions made upon us by the world.</em> That's the tradition that the American progressive thinkes the beginning of the 19th century adopted.</p>

<p>Emerson has a different view, his view is kind of an activist mind, for him, experience isn't just receiving the world. Emerson's view is that the mind goes out into the world, we make our experience in an active way (something there from Kant). <strong>Experience comes not by just humans being receptacles, but humans creating experience by actively living in the world.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>Grief too will make us idealists. In the death of my son, now more than two years ago, I seem to have lost a beautiful estate, — no more. I cannot get it nearer to me. If tomorrow I should be informed of the bankruptcy of my principal debtors, the loss of my property would be a great inconvenience to me, perhaps, for many years; but it would leave me as it found me, — neither better nor worse. Experience by Ralph Waldo Emerson</p>

<p> Life is a train of moods like a string of beads, and, as we pass through them, they prove to be many-colored lenses which paint the world their own hue, and each shows only what lies in its focus.</p></blockquote>

<p>There are times in our lives when we think that we are living a kind of banal existence. Everything is routine, that you know there, we go to work everyday or we go to school everyday, we have our meals at the same time, we see the same members of our family, our friends, our spouses, our lovers, whatever we're depending on our situation. And after while we've realized we're not feeling things. It's just going thorought life, going through the motions we might say. <strong>And sometimes we want a crisis, you want something big to happen, even if it's a bad thing, because it makes feel more alive, more vital.</strong></p>

<p>If you had some crisis, if you had a grief, you would at least wake up to the world, because you're living in the world without waking up to it. But grief will make us idealists. There are times when we think that we are away from the world and we hope that some huge even happens, even a horrible event, that will make us at least, feel the world.</p>

<p>But in fact, <strong>it's a mistate to think you need some huge experience, some trauma, to wake you up to the world.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>We animate what we can, and we see only what we animate.</p></blockquote>

<p>We make the world alive to us. We enliven the world.</p>

<hr />

<h2>[Human Kind] The Direction of History</h2>

<p>The interaction between different societies tooks all kind of forms, there were of course wars, trades, immigration from one society to the other, religion missionaries coming from one place to another.</p>

<p><strong>Does human history has a clear direction?</strong></p>

<p>All wars, trades, immigrations in history have a clear general direction and this direction is global unity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] Intensity and the Ordinary [humankind] There is No Justice in History]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/27/september-27-friday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/27/september-27-friday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<blockquote><p>It was a splendid mind. For if thought is like the keyboard of a piano, divided into so many notes, or like the alphabet is ranged in twenty-six letters all in order, then his splendid mind had one by one, firmly and accurately, until it had reached, say, the letter Q. He reached Q. Very few people in the whole of England ever reach Q... But after Q? What comes next?</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Web of love</strong> connects one with the other, not a logical deduction, but an intimacy born of affection and art.</p>

<blockquote><p>What is the meaning of life? That was all - a simple question; one that tended to close in on one with years. The great revelation had never come. The great revelation perhaps never did come. Instead there were little daily miracles, illuminations, matches struck unexpectedly in the dark; here was one.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>There is No Justice in History. Part 4</h2>

<p>The most common theory, which tries to explain the patriarchal system, points out that men are physically stronger than women and that men have used the greater physical force, physical power to force women into submission. That means men could monopolize certain economic tasks that demand hard manual labor, like plowing the fields and harvesting wheat or rice or whatever it is. And this gave men <strong>control of food production</strong> and gave them control of the economy which in turned translated into political power.</p>

<p>Problems of this theory: First of all the statement that men are stronger than women is true only on average and also it is true only with regard to certain types of strngths. Secondly, and more importantly, there simple is no direct relation between physical strength and social power smong homo sapiens, among humans.</p>

<p>Another theory explains that the dominance of men over women results not just from strength, but from something which is more complacted, <strong>from aggression</strong>. According to this theory, for millions of years of evolution, men have been evloving to become willing to engage in physical violence much more than women, and this is why throughout history warfare was a monopoly of mainly of men. Men -> war -> control civil society</p>

<p>Now recent studies indeed indicate that the hormonal and cognitive systems of men and women are somewhat different and that men, by nature, becuse of that more violent, more willing to use physical violence against others and therefore men are really better suited to serve as common soldiers than women.</p>

<p>The third most common theory for the rise of patriacrchal societies explain that through millions of years of evolution men and women evolved different survival and reproduction strategies. Men, competed with one another, for access to fetile women, for the opportunity to impregnate the women; therefore, if you wre a man your chance of reproducing and passing your genes to the next generation, depended above all on your ability to defeat other men, and to outperfom other men. A women on the other hand had no problem finding a man that was willing to impregnate her. However if the woman wanted her children to provide her with grandchildren she needed to carry them in her womb for nine long months and then nurture them and take care of them for years because it was not enought just to be impregnated. During all that time of pregnancy and child care woman had fewer opportunities to obtain food and woman reguired a lot of help. In order to ensure the survival of yourself and your children woman need a man.</p>

<p>According to this theory, as time went by, the feminine genes that made it to the next generation therefore belonged to the woman who were the most submissive caretakes, who agreed to everything the man wanted and who spent most of the time just taking care of the children. <em>The result of these different survival strategies according to the theory is that men have been programmed by millions of years of evolution to be ambitious and competitive and to excel in politics and business and so forth.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] Intensity and the Ordinary [humankind] There is No Justice in History]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/26/september-26-thursday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/26/september-26-thursday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Incapacity for belief. Critical thinking as being so important, how teaching people how to be critical and so that they actually will never fall for something that somebody else is selling them in less than sound way. But what happenes is you're so good at being ironic and critical or distant is you never have the capacity to like anything or to have strong affection for things because strong affection is usually not based in reason.</p>

<hr />

<h2>There is No Justice in History</h2>

<p>The Bible says in Deuteronomy chapter 22, verses 28 to 29:</p>

<blockquote><p>If a man meets a virgin who is not betrothed to anybody and seizes her and lies with her and they are found then the man who lay with her shall give to the father of the young women 50 sheckels.</p></blockquote>

<p>Child bearing, for example. has been considered woman's job in all human societies in history, for the simple reason that men don't have wombs. However, around this kind of hard kernel of universal biological differences between men and women, every society that we know of in history, managed to accumulate many cultural ideas and norms that have very little to do with biology. Societies associate a host of qualities and tasks and duties with masculinity (мужественность) and with femininity.</p>

<p>Chimpanzees use sex in order to cement political alliances, establish intimacy and diffuse tensions between individuals in the band and that doesn't result in the birth of little chimpanzees.</p>

<p><strong>Masculinuty</strong> - what you need to do, how you need to behave and talk and walk and dress in order to be a man. And this changes a lot from one culture to the other culture.</p>

<p>Males spend much of their lives engaged in all kinds of dramas and conflicts and competitions, just in order to prove that they are real man. And success is not guaranteed. Both females and males may fail to win a claim as real men and real women. Throughout the all of human history males have been willing to risk and even to sacrifice their lives, just so that people would say about them he is a real man.</p>

<p>No matter how a society define what it is to be a real man, and what is it to be a woman, to be a man was always better. This is what scholars mean when they speak about patriarchal societies and patriarchy.</p>

<p><strong>A patriarchai society</strong> is a society that values what is sees as masculine qualities more than it values what is considers to be feminine qualities. They educate males to be men; to think and act in a masculine way. But women, of course, they are still supposed to think and act and dress in a feminine way, and anyone who tries to change it will be punished. But patriarchai society doesn't reward men and women equaly. It rewards successful men with much more power and many more privileges than it rewards successful women.</p>

<p>With very few exceptions all known human societies in history, at least since agricultural evolution, were patriarchai societies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
