<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: knowledge | curious and driven]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/knowledge/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-27T10:50:27-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] Intensity and the Ordinary [humankind] There is No Justice in History]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/26/september-26-thursday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/26/september-26-thursday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Incapacity for belief. Critical thinking as being so important, how teaching people how to be critical and so that they actually will never fall for something that somebody else is selling them in less than sound way. But what happenes is you're so good at being ironic and critical or distant is you never have the capacity to like anything or to have strong affection for things because strong affection is usually not based in reason.</p>

<hr />

<h2>There is No Justice in History</h2>

<p>The Bible says in Deuteronomy chapter 22, verses 28 to 29:</p>

<blockquote><p>If a man meets a virgin who is not betrothed to anybody and seizes her and lies with her and they are found then the man who lay with her shall give to the father of the young women 50 sheckels.</p></blockquote>

<p>Child bearing, for example. has been considered woman's job in all human societies in history, for the simple reason that men don't have wombs. However, around this kind of hard kernel of universal biological differences between men and women, every society that we know of in history, managed to accumulate many cultural ideas and norms that have very little to do with biology. Societies associate a host of qualities and tasks and duties with masculinity (мужественность) and with femininity.</p>

<p>Chimpanzees use sex in order to cement political alliances, establish intimacy and diffuse tensions between individuals in the band and that doesn't result in the birth of little chimpanzees.</p>

<p><strong>Masculinuty</strong> - what you need to do, how you need to behave and talk and walk and dress in order to be a man. And this changes a lot from one culture to the other culture.</p>

<p>Males spend much of their lives engaged in all kinds of dramas and conflicts and competitions, just in order to prove that they are real man. And success is not guaranteed. Both females and males may fail to win a claim as real men and real women. Throughout the all of human history males have been willing to risk and even to sacrifice their lives, just so that people would say about them he is a real man.</p>

<p>No matter how a society define what it is to be a real man, and what is it to be a woman, to be a man was always better. This is what scholars mean when they speak about patriarchal societies and patriarchy.</p>

<p><strong>A patriarchai society</strong> is a society that values what is sees as masculine qualities more than it values what is considers to be feminine qualities. They educate males to be men; to think and act in a masculine way. But women, of course, they are still supposed to think and act and dress in a feminine way, and anyone who tries to change it will be punished. But patriarchai society doesn't reward men and women equaly. It rewards successful men with much more power and many more privileges than it rewards successful women.</p>

<p>With very few exceptions all known human societies in history, at least since agricultural evolution, were patriarchai societies.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] Intensity and the Ordinary [humankind] There is No Justice in History [thinkagain] Close Analysis]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/25/september-25-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/25/september-25-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h2>Art, Loss, and Forgiveness</h2>

<p>Read <a href="http://ebooks.adelaide.edu.au/w/woolf/virginia/w91t/">To the lighthouse</a> by Virginia Woolf.</p>

<p><strong>Virgina Woolf</strong> was part of a group that has stimulated the imagination of historians and literary critics for a long time, the <em>Bloomsbury group</em>. They saw middle class morality as hypoctritical in many cases and they wanted to go beyond that, although they were very much middle class, they go beyond convention in terms of friendship, in terms of sexuality, in terms of art making, to find something that would be more meaningful and less violent and less hypoctritical.</p>

<p>Intrinsic goods like friendship, beauty, art, love stood on their own and commitment to them structured your other beliefs, rather than your other beliefs leading you to have a commitment to friendship or love or beauty.</p>

<p>Moore was an analytic philosopher. But one of the things he tried to show was that no matter how much precision you use, how much <strong>scientifically</strong> organized argument you use, <strong>you could not actually define the good.</strong></p>

<p>Goodness is indefinable, goodness is not reducible to anything else.
Learning to draw, to play the piano, to read a poem didn't have to be justified in terms of how much money you would make later on. Because actually no one says that making money is the highest good. And Moor and the the Bloomsbury group said no, no, art is its own thing, it doesn't have to be justified in other terms, so too friendship, so too love.</p>

<hr />

<h2>There is No Justice in History</h2>

<p>Your classify people into several different categories and then treat people according to the category to which they belongs without really bothering to know who they are and what their true abilities and true personality is.</p>

<p>For example, in traditional Hindu society if you are going to marry, say, you're looking for a potential bride or groom. The first thing and mose important thing that you want to know about this person, your potential husband or wife is to which caste they belong.</p>

<p>Similarly, today in the world capitalists believe that the reason hierarchy of wealth and this hierarchy of wealth reflects real differences in the ability and qualities of people. Capitalists at least, many of them believe that the rich have more money and privileges because they are more intelligent and hard working and this is how they became rich. So according to the capitilist no one should be bothered if the rich get better health care, better education and nutrition because they have earned it.</p>

<p>Most of the abilities of people have to be nurtured and developed even if somebody is born with a particular talent. Like playing football, or doing business. That talent will usually remain latent if it is not fostered and exircised. And not all people in a particular society get the same chance to cultivate and exercise their abilities. Weather or not they will have an opportunity to do so will usually depend on their place within the imagined hierarchy of that society.</p>

<p>Even if people belonging to different classes somehow develop exactly the same abilities, still they are unlikely to enjoy equal chances of success because they will have to play the game by different rules.</p>

<p>People have been given by a long evolutionary process a fear of polluting themselves by coming in contact with all kinds of things that might cause them diseases, like dead bodies, rotten corpses or bad food. Then, all kinds of religions and social systems "hijacked" this biological mechanisms of developing disgust towards something and turned it agains certain groups of people.</p>

<p>Racial system in American was caused by European invasion and conquest of America in the early modern period, and more importantly, the importation by the European conquerors of millions of African slaves to work in the mines and plantations of America.</p>

<p><strong>Why they didn't employ simple the local indians</strong> is that the Europeans brought with them a lot of unfamiliar illnesses, diseases, to American and the Indians died in millions. More than 90% of the population of the America, died within a century of the arrival of Europeans. So they had to import people from someplace else to work in mines.</p>

<p><strong>Why they didn't employ people from Europe or India or China?</strong> <strong>First</strong> of all, Africa was closer to American than Asia, so it was cheaper to import slaves from Senegal than to import slaves from Vietnam. <strong>Secondly</strong>, in Africa was already existed a very well developed slave trade. Mainly muslim slave traders North Africa and the Middle East developed in the previous centuries a lively trade in African slaves which were exported from Central Africa to North Africa and the Middle East. <strong>Third</strong>, and most important reason, is that American plantations of sugar, cotton, coffee and so forth, were mostly located in tropical areas of America. Like Tahiti and Brazil, Lousiana and Virginia. And these tropical areas were plagued by tropical diseases such as malaria and yellow fever which had originated in Africa. So, African had immune to this diseases and it was much better for investors buying an African slave who was already resistant to malaria and yellow fever, than buying, say, an Irish slave who would die within six months.</p>

<p>European theologians said that Africans descended from Ham, son of the biblical Noah and Ham was cursed by his father Noah that his offspring would be slaves. And this is why it's okay to enslave Africans.</p>

<p>One of the sad truths about history is that over time, unjust discrimination against a particular group of people often gets worse, not better. Money, very often comes to money, and poverty comes to poverty. Most sociopolitical hierarchies in human history, they lack any objective biological and logical basis. They are nothing but a perpetuation of accidental events which are supported by imagined stories that people invented over time.</p>

<hr />

<h2>Close Analysis</h2>

<p>Reason Marker = R
Conclusion Marker = C
Assuring Term = A
Guarding Term = G
Discounting Term = D
Positive Evaluative Term = E+
Negative Evaluative Term = E-</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] Building Pyramids. Part 3 [thinkagain] Standard Form]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/19/september-19-thursday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-19T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/19/september-19-thursday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Food alone is not enough, you also need an imagined order, but we need one more thing - technique for storing and processing huge amounts of information. After Agricultural Revolution as human societies began to grow larger and larger, who things happened.</p>

<p>First, the amounts of necessary information grew (run village with 5000 people versus band with 50). Second, if you really want to run a big town or kingdom, you need to store and process not only larger amounts of information but also a completely new kinds of infromation, for which the average human brain is ill-adopted - <strong>monotonous mathematical data (numbers)</strong>. Mathematical data is vital (taxes, debt, fines, credit).</p>

<p>Writing is a method for storing and processing information and by using not our neurons in the brain, but by using material signs of all kinds and shapes. Writing was invented not in order to write poetry or philosophy with history because this could be done withour writing. The purpose was to store and process mathematical data for which the Sumerians invented the first script, the first system of writing.</p>

<hr />

<h2>[thinkagain] Standard Form</h2>

<p>Because I am a professor, I teach classes.
I teach classes because I am a professor.</p>

<p>vs</p>

<p>I teach classes, so I am a professor.</p>

<p>(1) Premise
(2) Premise</p>

<hr />

<p> .
. . (3) Conclusion (from 1-2)</p>

<p><strong>Example:</strong></p>

<p>(1) I am a professor</p>

<hr />

<p> .
. . (2) I teach classes (from 1)</p>

<p>(1) I teach classes</p>

<hr />

<p> .
. . (2) I am a professor (from 1)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] Intensity and the Ordinary [humankind] Building Pyramids. Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/18/september-18-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/18/september-18-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For Freud and Civilization's of discontents <strong>guilt is a modern problem</strong>. As we have modernization, as we have a more and more sophisticated society <em>we have a greater and greater chance of the explosion of unsatisfied</em>.</p>

<p>Freud is no friend of anarchism or hypermorality, no friend of socialism, because he thinks all of these are introducing new ideals that will be very difficult to live by.</p>

<blockquote><p>Thus I have not the courage to rise up before my fellow-men as a prophet, and I bow to their reproach that I can offer them no consolation: for at bottom that is what they are demanding - the wildest revolutionaries no less passionately than the most virtuous believers. Civilization and Its Discontents</p></blockquote>

<p>Freud wants to escape the pursuit of meaning through ideals. He doesn't want us to strive to live on a plain that is divorced from our animal natures, divorced from instinct. He doesn't want us to try to find a mode of consolation that obscures who we are. Because if we obscure who we are, then we create another source of suffering.</p>

<p><em>There is no perfect life for Freud, because there's no one good way of living. But we can figure out how to make ourselves suffer less and that would be a significant achievement.</em> All our desires are full of conflict.</p>

<hr />

<h2>Building Pyramids</h2>

<p>Armies, police forces, courts and prisons are ceaselessly at work forcing people to act in accordance with the imagined order. A single priest often does the work of 100 soldiers far more cheaply and effectively. The priest convinces you to really believe this story, and then you don't need all the soldiers and police forces to keep you in order. And this was the key for really creating stable social orders.</p>

<p><em>How exactly do you cause people to really believe in an imagined order, such as Christianity, Democracy or Capitalism?</em></p>

<p> Three main factors that prevent people from realizing that the order which organizes their lives and their society exists only in the imagination. We try to link it with the actual material reality which surrounds us.</p>

<p> Many people believe that every human being is an individual whose worth, whose true value does not depent on his or her position in the social hierarchy and does not depend on what other people think about you. The main idea of individualism is that each one os us, have within ourselves some kind of brillian ray of light that gives value and meaning to our lives.</p>

<p>The imagined order also shapes our deepest desires and wishes. Most people do not wish to accept the fact that the order governing their lives is imaginary, because it's the imginary order that control and shapes the most fundamental wishes of the people.</p>

<p><strong>Example:</strong> Many people today dream about going on vacation to some other country. But there is nothing natural or obvious about this desire. People today spend a great deal of time and effort and money on vacation abroad, because they have programmed by the main stories of their societies to want such things. <strong>People today are true believers in the stories of what scholars call the <em>romantic consumerism</em>.</strong></p>

<p><strong>Romantic consumerism</strong> is one of the most powerful stories today in the world, is a mesh, is a combination between two of the dominant late modern ideologies: <em>romanticism</em> and <em>consumerism</em>.</p>

<p><strong>Romanticism</strong> tells us that in order to make the most of your life, of your human potential, you must have as many different experiences as you can. You must open yourself to a wide spectrum of emotions. You must sample various kinds of relationships. You must try all kinds of different foods. <strong>The best way of doing it is to break free from your daily routine, leave behind your familiar neighborhood and city, and go travel in distant land.</strong></p>

<p><strong>Consumerism</strong> tells us that in order to be happy - you must consume as many products and sevices as possible. If you feel what something is missing in your life, then you probably need to buy a new product, like a new car or new clothe. Or you need to buy some kind of service, yoga class or psychologie retreat, but <strong>you need to buy something to be really happy</strong>.</p>

<p>Differenece between realities objective, subjective and inter-subjective.</p>

<p><strong>Objective</strong> - something that exists independently of human consciousness and of what human believe and invent and tell one another. Example: radio activity - is not a story that people invented and tell one another, existed and influenced people long before anybody knew about it.</p>

<p><strong>Subjective</strong> - is something that exists depending on the consciosness and beliefs of a single individual and it will disappear or change if that particular individual changes his or her beliefs. Exmaple: many children believe in the existence of imaginery friend that only the child himself can see and can talk to. And usually as a child grows up, he stops believing in this imaginary friend.</p>

<p><strong>Inter-subjective</strong> - is something that exists within the communication network that link the subjective consciosness of many individuals. If a single individual changes his/her beliefs or even dies, it is of little importance. However, if most individuals in the network die or change their beliefs, then the inter-subjective phenomenon will mutate and change or completely disappear. Example: Gods, nations, human rights, money, corporations and so on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] Intensity and the Ordinary [humankind] Building Pyramids]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/17/september-17-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/17/september-17-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Freud established his credibility as an enlightenment thinker, he goes on to talk about why the only thing you can really look at scienitifcally is the pleasure principle. <strong>Three sources of suffering - own body, the external world and other people</strong>.</p>

<p>He says, so many other writers, whether they're religious writers or philosophical writers or politicals, social commentators, what they really want to do is instead of facing what really causes us sorrow, and pain, they want actually to give us consolation (утешение). <strong>Consolation</strong> is not what we should pursue, it is awful thing, because it disguises where our suffering comes from and makes it harder for us to deal with these <strong>sources of suffering</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>Life, as we find it, is too hard for us; it brings us too many pains, disappointments and impossible tasks. In order to bear it we cannot dispense with palliative (паллиативный, смягчающий) measures. Civilization and Its Discontents</p></blockquote>

<p>It means we come up with some kind of drugs, so we don't have to deal with life as it really is.</p>

<blockquote><p>... we cannot fail to be struck by the similarity between the process of civiliation and the libidinal (sexual desire) development of the individual. ... it is impossible to overlook the extent to which civilization is built upon a renunciation (formal rejection of something) of instinct, how much it presupposes precisely the non-satisfaction... of powerful instincts.</p></blockquote>

<p>Every time you have people say, well, love your neighbor, be to strangers, all that, you always find some scapegoat (a person who is blamed for the wrongdoing, mistakes козел отпущения) that you can take your rage out on. Every time you ask people to be sweet and kind as a rule, they will find something to attack.</p>

<blockquote><p>In this respect the Jewish people, scattered everywhere, have rendered the most useful service to the civiliations of the countries that have been their hosts; but unfortunately all the massacres of the Jews in the Middle Ages did not suffice to make that period more peaceful and secure for their Christian fellows. Civilization and Its Discontents.</p></blockquote>

<p>Not only do we find scapegoats out there that we can hate and attack and turn our aggression inward as a result of our guilt. As we become more civilized we have more and more occasions to feel we're not living up to our ideals, <strong>become twisted and wracked by guilt, because we're not living up to the expectations we've created for ourselves. We're not studying enough, we're not working hard enought, we're not making enought money.</strong></p>

<hr />
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
