<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: knowledge | nameless]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/knowledge/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-08-08T14:41:24-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science August 8th, 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/08/science-august-8th/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-08T14:38:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/08/science-august-8th</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p>Новое исследование показало, что транскраниальная магнитная стимуляция (неинвазивно       стимуляция коры головного мозга при помощи коротких магнитных импульсов) может изменять     организацию мозга, что в свою очередь может помочь в борьбе с депрессией, эпилепсией и       звон в ушах (tinnitus).</p></li>
<li><p>Колоссальное исследование показало, что генетически модифицированная мышь с              отсутствующим протеином TRAP-1 проживает дольше и в тоже время наблюдается значительно        уменьшение болезней связанных с возрастом, такие как дегенерация тканей и избыток веса.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/rewired-mice-show-signs-of-longer-lives-with-fewer-age-related-illnesses">"source"</a></p></li>
<li><p>Инженеры разработали технологию под названием "Wi-Fi обратного рассеивания", которая        используя присутствующие окружающие сигналы как источник энергии для безбатарейных            устройств.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9250171/Researchers_promote_battery_free_Wi_Fi_technology">"source"</a></p></li>
<li><p>IBM объявило о радикально новой архитектуре чипов, которые могут эмулировать структуры      головного мозга и уже достигли эмуляции 1 миллиона нейронов и более 256 миллионов          программируемых синапсисов.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/ibm-launches-functioning-brain-inspired-chip">"source"</a></p></li>
<li><p>Исследовадетил из MIT, Adobe и Microsoft смогли реконструировать аудио разговор просто        снимая на видео и анализируя малейшие вибрации на объектах (например снимая на видео         пакет с чипсами находящийся в 5 метрах за звуконепроницаемым стеклом).</p>

<p><a href="http://time.com/3080126/mit-potato-chip-bag-spying/">"source"</a></p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science August 3, 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/03/science-august-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-03T17:36:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/03/science-august-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p>Tesla Motors подписала договор с Panasonic о строительстве               гигафабрики стоимость 5 миллиардов долларов, что позволит сократить   стоимость на 30% и производить больше аккамуляторов, чем все            фабрики (производящие литий-ионные аккамуляторы) вместе взятые.</p></li>
<li><p>Исследователи создали наночастицы (диаметр 15 нанометров), которые       могут доставлять лекарство или другие молекулы в заданные живые      клетки.</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://khakimov.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/X5EzUyDrcjo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p></li>
<li><p>Hubble телескоп обнаружил самую отделенную линзированную (lensing?)    галактику. Насколько я понимаю, гравитационной линзой называют            массивные тела или системы тел, искревляющие своим гравитационным      полем направление распространения электромагнитного излучения.             Приблизительный вес в 180 миллиардов раз больше, чем наше солнце.        Свет от новой галактики был в пути 9.6 миллиардов лет, чтобы          достигнуть нашей планеты.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.redorbit.com/media/uploads/2014/08/farthest-cosmic-lens-617x416.jpg" alt="" /></p></li>
<li><p>Вакцина против малярии предохраняет детей от заражения на 18 месяцев   . Еще один шаг ближе к борьбе с малярией у детей в Африке, но             вопрос о цене остается открытым.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.techtimes.com/articles/11632/20140801/malaria-vaccine-rts-s-as01-protects-children-for-18-months-when-will-it-be-ready.htm"></a></p></li>
<li><p>Инженеры разработали прототип таблеточного экрана, который              компенсирует проблемы со зрением за счет добавления тонкого             микроточечного фильтра повышающий резкость изображения.</p>

<p><img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/76625000/jpg/_76625878_eyeglassdisplay-macaroons670.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-28562432"></a></p></li>
<li><p>Новый источник стволовых клеток обнаружен в зубах.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.kinja-img.com/gawker-media/image/upload/s--tRUdUMlV--/c_fit,fl_progressive,q_80,w_636/aawpvrec67dbip89h7yo.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://gizmodo.com/there-are-cells-inside-teeth-that-can-turn-back-into-st-1614066776"></a></p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] The discrovery of Ignorance. Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/22/october-22-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-22T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/22/october-22-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Until the early modern period humans all over the world invested very little effort in scientific research, because they doubted their ability to obtain new medical or military or economic powers. Kings and emperors certainly gave money to education and scholarship but the main aim of scholarship in the pre-modern world was to preserve existing capabilities and not to acquire new one. The typical king gave money to priests, and philosophers, and poets in the hope that they would legitimize his rule and maintain the social order.</p>

<p>In the last five centuries howevers, humans increasingly came to believe that they could gain new, more and more powers by investing money and resources in scientific research.</p>

<p>Since cognitive revolutions, humans have always tried to figure out how the universe works. Out ancestors, thousands and even ten of thousands of years ago, put great deal of time and effort in trying to discover the rules that govern the natural world around them. So, what is so <em>special and different</em> about <strong>modern science</strong>?</p>

<p>Modern science differs from all previous traditions of knowledge in three critical ways:</p>

<ul>
<li>If differs its willingness to admit ignorance. Modern science is based on the admission that we do not know everything. Even more importantly, modern science accepts that the things that we think we know, could still be proven wrong as we gain more knowledge.</li>
<li>The second unique characteristic is the centrality of observation and mathematics. Gathering observations on the world, and using mathematical tools to connect these observations into comprehensive theories.</li>
<li>The third unique feature of modern science is that it aims to acquire new powers. It uses theories in order to acquire new powers, and in particular in order to develop new technologies. The real aim of modern science is not truth, it is power.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] Postmodern Identities. Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/21/october-21-monday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-21T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/21/october-21-monday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Judith Butler and Slavoj Zizek, who are both very active and in some respects in the prime of their careers. Judith Butler started her carier with the work on French Hegelianism and her dissertation had to do with the status of Hegel in modern France. She moved on to work on gender and sexuality in a book called <strong>Gender Trouble</strong> which really was a game changer in the field of women's studie gay and lesbian studies and queer studie as it came to be called later.</p>

<blockquote><p>To understand gender as a historical category, however, is to accept that gender, understood as one way of culturally configuring a body, is open to a continual remaking, and that 'anatomy' and 'sex' are not without cultural framing. <strong>Undoing Gender</strong></p>

<p>If gender is a kind of doing, an incessant activity performed, in part, without one's knowing and without one's willing, it is not for that reason automatic or mechanical. On the contrary, it is a practice of improvisation within a scene of constraint.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>[Humankind] The Law of Religion. Part 4</h2>

<p>Humanism is the belief that Homo sapiens has an unique and sacred nature which is fundamentally different from the nature of all the other animals and of all other phenomena in the universe. Humanists believe that the unique nature of Homo sapiense is the most important thing in the world and it is this that determines the meaning of everything that happens in the universe.</p>

<p><strong>Liberal Humanism</strong> which believes that humanity is a quality of individual humans. According to Liberals, the sacred nature of humanity resides within each and every individual Homo sapiens. And therefore, the supreme values of the world is the liberty of individuals.</p>

<p><strong>Socialist Humanism</strong> believes that humanity is collective and not individualistic. Socialists hold as sacred not the inner voice of each individual, but the species Homo sapiens as a whole, seeks equality between all humans. Inequality is the worst blasphemy (богохульство) against the sanctity of humanity, because inequality privileges peripheral qualities of humans over their common universal essence. For example, when the rich are given privileges which are withheld from the poor, it means that we value money more than we value the universal essence of all humans which is similar for everybody, for rich and poor alike.</p>

<p><strong>Evolutionary humanism</strong> (the most famous representatives were the Nazis). Nazis too believed in the sanctity of humanity. They had a different defenition of humanity than the Liberals and the Socialists. The Nazis were deeply influenced by the theory of evolution, believed that humankind is not something universal and eternal and unchanging. Rather, they believed that it is a specie of animals which can evolve or degenerate in accordance with the theory of evolution. The main ambition of the Nazis was to protect human kind from the generation extinction and encourage the evolution of human kind into super men.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] The Law of Religion. Part 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/16/october-16-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/16/october-16-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A religion that recognizes the legitimacy of other faith, implies either that its god is not the supreme power of the universe or that it reveived from the one and only god, only part of the universal truth. "If our religion is true no other religion can also simultaneously be true."</p>

<p><strong>Dualistic religions</strong> - are religions that believe in the existence not of one supreme Good but of two opposing powers, good and evil. Dualism believes that evil is an independent power, which is not created by the good god and is not subordinate to it.</p>

<p>Wars, plague, death, suffer - this is God's way of allowing for human free will. If there was no evil in the world, humans could not choose between good and evel; and hence, there would be no free will.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
