<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: knowledge | nameless]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/knowledge/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-02-02T12:00:09-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science August 15th, 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/17/science-august-15th/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-17T18:05:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/17/science-august-15th</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Технологии на этой неделе (8 - 15 августа 2014)</p>

<ol>
<li><p>Ученые создали лазер, который может определять взрывчатые вещества и наркотики на             расстоянии одного километра. Технология использует <a href="https://ru.wikipedia.org/wiki/%D0%9A%D0%BE%D0%BC%D0%B1%D0%B8%D0%BD%D0%B0%D1%86%D0%B8%D0%BE%D0%BD%D0%BD%D0%BE%D0%B5_%D1%80%D0%B0%D1%81%D1%81%D0%B5%D1%8F%D0%BD%D0%B8%D0%B5_%D1%81%D0%B2%D0%B5%D1%82%D0%B0">комбинационное рассеяние света</a> (грубо говоря, используется спектроскопия, когда можно видеть изменения частоты излучения)</p>

<p><a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/8/11/5991259/scientists-made-a-laser-than-can-detect-explosives-from-half-a-mile">Scientists made a laser that can detect explosives from half a mile away</a></p></li>
<li><p>Исследователи разработали временную татуировку способную отслеживать тренировочный          прогресс и одновременно производить из пота достаточно мощности для зарядки небольших        электронных устройств.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2014/08/140813103134.htm">Temporary tattoo biobatteries produce power from sweat </a></p></li>
<li><p>Ученые из Гарварда создали самоорганизующийся рой из 1024 микро-роботов (управляймый       через IR).</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://khakimov.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/xK54Bu9HFRw" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>

<p><a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/a-self-organizing-thousand-robot-swarm">A self-organizing thousand-robot swarm</a></p></li>
<li><p>Крупная Южно-Корейская корпорация Daewoo Shipbuilding начало оснащать рабочих одеваемым     экзоскелетами, которые позволят им дополнительно поднимать до 120 кг.</p>

<p><img src="http://static.ddmcdn.com/gif/blogs/dnews-files-2014-08-robotic-exoskeleton-shipbuilding-670-jpg.jpg" alt="exoskeleton" /></p>

<p><a href="http://news.discovery.com/tech/robotics/exoskeleton-suit-workers-don-suit-for-heavy-lifting-140805.htm">Exoskeleton First: Workers Don Suit for Heavy Lifting</a></p></li>
<li><p>Samsung заключил сделку о покупке компании SmartThings (IOT) за 200 миллионов долларов,    раскрыв планы о использовании их открытой платформы, которая уже насчитывает 1000             совместимых устройств, чтобы объеденить и наделить интеллектом все окружающие нас            устройства.</p>

<p><img src="http://images.bwbx.io/cms/2013-02-14/tech_smartthings08__01__630x420.jpg" alt="smart things" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.forbes.com/sites/aarontilley/2014/08/14/samsung-smartthings-acquisition-2/">Samsung Acquires SmartThings, A Fast-Growing Home Automation Startup</a></p></li>
<li><p>Вживленные нервные стволовые клетки (neuronal stem cells, наверное имеется ввиду            стволовая клетка, которая характеризуется своей способностью дифференцироваться в          несколько типов клеток с помощью внешних стимулов из окружащего состояния) успешно           создают нейроны и синапсисы став функциональной частью головного мозга мыши, повышая       надежды на возможность создания способов лечения нейродегенеративных заболеваний, таких   как "Болезнь Паркинсона".</p>

<p><img src="http://www.kurzweilai.net/images/transplanted-neural-cells.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/implanted-neuronal-stem-cells-generate-neurons-and-synapses-becoming-a-functioning-part-of-mouse-brain">Implanted neuronal stem cells generate neurons and synapses, becoming a functioning part of mouse brain</a></p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science August 8th, 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/08/science-august-8th/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-08T14:38:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/08/science-august-8th</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p>Новое исследование показало, что транскраниальная магнитная стимуляция (неинвазивно       стимуляция коры головного мозга при помощи коротких магнитных импульсов) может изменять     организацию мозга, что в свою очередь может помочь в борьбе с депрессией, эпилепсией и       звон в ушах (tinnitus).</p>

<p><a href="http://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2014/08/140806025318.htm">source</a></p></li>
<li><p>Колоссальное исследование показало, что генетически модифицированная мышь с              отсутствующим протеином TRAP-1 проживает дольше и в тоже время наблюдается значительно        уменьшение болезней связанных с возрастом, такие как дегенерация тканей и избыток веса.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/rewired-mice-show-signs-of-longer-lives-with-fewer-age-related-illnesses">source</a></p></li>
<li><p>Инженеры разработали технологию под названием "Wi-Fi обратного рассеивания", которая        используя присутствующие окружающие сигналы как источник энергии для безбатарейных            устройств.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.computerworld.com/s/article/9250171/Researchers_promote_battery_free_Wi_Fi_technology">source</a></p></li>
<li><p>IBM объявило о радикально новой архитектуре чипов, которые могут эмулировать структуры      головного мозга и уже достигли эмуляции 1 миллиона нейронов и более 256 миллионов          программируемых синапсисов.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.kurzweilai.net/ibm-launches-functioning-brain-inspired-chip">source</a></p></li>
<li><p>Исследовадетил из MIT, Adobe и Microsoft смогли реконструировать аудио разговор просто        снимая на видео и анализируя малейшие вибрации на объектах (например снимая на видео         пакет с чипсами находящийся в 5 метрах за звуконепроницаемым стеклом).</p>

<p><a href="http://time.com/3080126/mit-potato-chip-bag-spying/">source</a></p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Science August 3, 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/03/science-august-3/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-03T17:36:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2014/08/03/science-august-3</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<ol>
<li><p>Tesla Motors подписала договор с Panasonic о строительстве               гигафабрики стоимость 5 миллиардов долларов, что позволит сократить   стоимость на 30% и производить больше аккамуляторов, чем все            фабрики (производящие литий-ионные аккамуляторы) вместе взятые.</p></li>
<li><p>Исследователи создали наночастицы (диаметр 15 нанометров), которые       могут доставлять лекарство или другие молекулы в заданные живые      клетки.</p>

<p><iframe width="560" height="315" src="http://khakimov.github.com//www.youtube.com/embed/X5EzUyDrcjo" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe></p></li>
<li><p>Hubble телескоп обнаружил самую отделенную линзированную (lensing?)    галактику. Насколько я понимаю, гравитационной линзой называют            массивные тела или системы тел, искревляющие своим гравитационным      полем направление распространения электромагнитного излучения.             Приблизительный вес в 180 миллиардов раз больше, чем наше солнце.        Свет от новой галактики был в пути 9.6 миллиардов лет, чтобы          достигнуть нашей планеты.</p>

<p><img src="http://www.redorbit.com/media/uploads/2014/08/farthest-cosmic-lens-617x416.jpg" alt="" /></p></li>
<li><p>Вакцина против малярии предохраняет детей от заражения на 18 месяцев   . Еще один шаг ближе к борьбе с малярией у детей в Африке, но             вопрос о цене остается открытым.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.techtimes.com/articles/11632/20140801/malaria-vaccine-rts-s-as01-protects-children-for-18-months-when-will-it-be-ready.htm"></a></p></li>
<li><p>Инженеры разработали прототип таблеточного экрана, который              компенсирует проблемы со зрением за счет добавления тонкого             микроточечного фильтра повышающий резкость изображения.</p>

<p><img src="http://news.bbcimg.co.uk/media/images/76625000/jpg/_76625878_eyeglassdisplay-macaroons670.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-28562432"></a></p></li>
<li><p>Новый источник стволовых клеток обнаружен в зубах.</p>

<p><img src="http://i.kinja-img.com/gawker-media/image/upload/s--tRUdUMlV--/c_fit,fl_progressive,q_80,w_636/aawpvrec67dbip89h7yo.jpg" alt="" /></p>

<p><a href="http://gizmodo.com/there-are-cells-inside-teeth-that-can-turn-back-into-st-1614066776"></a></p></li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[humankind] The discrovery of Ignorance. Part 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/22/october-22-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-22T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/22/october-22-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Until the early modern period humans all over the world invested very little effort in scientific research, because they doubted their ability to obtain new medical or military or economic powers. Kings and emperors certainly gave money to education and scholarship but the main aim of scholarship in the pre-modern world was to preserve existing capabilities and not to acquire new one. The typical king gave money to priests, and philosophers, and poets in the hope that they would legitimize his rule and maintain the social order.</p>

<p>In the last five centuries howevers, humans increasingly came to believe that they could gain new, more and more powers by investing money and resources in scientific research.</p>

<p>Since cognitive revolutions, humans have always tried to figure out how the universe works. Out ancestors, thousands and even ten of thousands of years ago, put great deal of time and effort in trying to discover the rules that govern the natural world around them. So, what is so <em>special and different</em> about <strong>modern science</strong>?</p>

<p>Modern science differs from all previous traditions of knowledge in three critical ways:</p>

<ul>
<li>If differs its willingness to admit ignorance. Modern science is based on the admission that we do not know everything. Even more importantly, modern science accepts that the things that we think we know, could still be proven wrong as we gain more knowledge.</li>
<li>The second unique characteristic is the centrality of observation and mathematics. Gathering observations on the world, and using mathematical tools to connect these observations into comprehensive theories.</li>
<li>The third unique feature of modern science is that it aims to acquire new powers. It uses theories in order to acquire new powers, and in particular in order to develop new technologies. The real aim of modern science is not truth, it is power.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/september-30-monday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/september-30-monday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two person who were important for contemporary philosophy Ralph Waldo Emerson and Ludwin Wittgenstein. Emerson is a key figure in American intellectual history, cultural history, but until pretty recently wasn't seen as a key figure in philosophy. Often flowery (витиеватый) writer, he is a writer of wonderful sentences one of the most quotable authors in American history. Emerson's philosophical contribution to American culture as an author whose importance rivals that of Nietzsche and of Heidegger both of whom were influenced by Emerson.</p>

<p>Emerson was born during the presidency of Thoman Jefferson, so very early in the nineteenth century, lived a long life, he was at some point a minister and left the pulpit, because of a crisis of faith, not so much in the divine being but in instritutionalized religion and became an eassayst and lecturer. Emerson had audiences of thousands of people around the contry who were following his intellectual excursions via lectures in towns across the United States. His departure from enlightenment tradition as it had been imported into the United Stated is really key.</p>

<p><em>The englightenment tradition in the United States was very much indebted to the Lockian Tradition, that is the view that all our ideas come from sensations that we are receptacle of stimuli from the world and that our ideas and then our belief and our work comes as we process the stimulation, the sensation that comes into us. In some ways, thinking of us as a blank slate and having these impressions made upon us by the world.</em> That's the tradition that the American progressive thinkes the beginning of the 19th century adopted.</p>

<p>Emerson has a different view, his view is kind of an activist mind, for him, experience isn't just receiving the world. Emerson's view is that the mind goes out into the world, we make our experience in an active way (something there from Kant). <strong>Experience comes not by just humans being receptacles, but humans creating experience by actively living in the world.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>Grief too will make us idealists. In the death of my son, now more than two years ago, I seem to have lost a beautiful estate, — no more. I cannot get it nearer to me. If tomorrow I should be informed of the bankruptcy of my principal debtors, the loss of my property would be a great inconvenience to me, perhaps, for many years; but it would leave me as it found me, — neither better nor worse. Experience by Ralph Waldo Emerson</p>

<p> Life is a train of moods like a string of beads, and, as we pass through them, they prove to be many-colored lenses which paint the world their own hue, and each shows only what lies in its focus.</p></blockquote>

<p>There are times in our lives when we think that we are living a kind of banal existence. Everything is routine, that you know there, we go to work everyday or we go to school everyday, we have our meals at the same time, we see the same members of our family, our friends, our spouses, our lovers, whatever we're depending on our situation. And after while we've realized we're not feeling things. It's just going thorought life, going through the motions we might say. <strong>And sometimes we want a crisis, you want something big to happen, even if it's a bad thing, because it makes feel more alive, more vital.</strong></p>

<p>If you had some crisis, if you had a grief, you would at least wake up to the world, because you're living in the world without waking up to it. But grief will make us idealists. There are times when we think that we are away from the world and we hope that some huge even happens, even a horrible event, that will make us at least, feel the world.</p>

<p>But in fact, <strong>it's a mistate to think you need some huge experience, some trauma, to wake you up to the world.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>We animate what we can, and we see only what we animate.</p></blockquote>

<p>We make the world alive to us. We enliven the world.</p>

<hr />

<h2>[Human Kind] The Direction of History</h2>

<p>The interaction between different societies tooks all kind of forms, there were of course wars, trades, immigration from one society to the other, religion missionaries coming from one place to another.</p>

<p><strong>Does human history has a clear direction?</strong></p>

<p>All wars, trades, immigrations in history have a clear general direction and this direction is global unity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
