<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: knowledge | curious and driven]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/knowledge/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-07T20:39:27-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] From Critical Theory to Postmodernism [humankind] Imperial Visions]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/07/october-07-monday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/07/october-07-monday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Horkheimer and Adorno writing in the Nazi period what problem are they trying to address? What issue are they trying to explain?</p>

<p>They are trying to understand the attractions of fascism and Nazism, why the working classes don't rebel against their owners of capital, why they don't rebel against the massive corporations or the political parties that feed them.</p>

<p>They saw this really nefarious (гнусный, бесчестный) globalization as a product of enlightenment. They asw modernity and enlughtenment joining hands to create a new universal myth that entrapped us with its appeal while controlling us and diminising our freedom at every step.</p>

<blockquote><p>Englightenment, understood in the widest sense as the advance of thought, has always aimed at liberating human beings from fear and installing them as masters. Yet the wholly enlightened earth is radiant with triumphant calamity. Enlightenment's program was the disenchantment of the world. Horkheimer and Adorno</p>

<p>Techonology is the essence of this knowlegde. It aims to produce neither concepts nor images, nor the joy of understanding, but method, exploitation of the labor of others... What human beings seek to learn from nature is how to use it to dominate wholly both it and human beings. Nothing else counts.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>Imperial Visions</h2>

<p>What empire is? It is a political order which has two very important characteristics:</p>

<ol>
<li><p>rules over a significant number of distinct peoples, each possessing a different cultural identity and a separate territory.</p></li>
<li><p>It has flexible borders and a potentially unlimited appetite.</p></li>
</ol>


<p>It's very common today to hear that in the long run, it is not possible to rule effectively over a large number of conquered people, that empires are doomed to failure and to collapse. The second main objection to empires is not only that they don't work, but also that they are evil.</p>

<p>Empire has been the world's most common form of political organization for the last 2500 years. Emires are a very stable, irrelatively, when compared to other form of goverments, empire is very stable form of government.</p>

<p>Most empires have been collapsed either because of external invasion of external enemies or because of a split within the ruling elite itself.</p>

<p>The standard imperial toolkit with which you build and maintain an empire includes war, enslavement, deportation and genocide.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/03/october-03-thursday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/03/october-03-thursday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By playing with new devices, you understand how to us it.</p>

<blockquote><p>We got to know the nature of calculating by learning to calculate. Ludwig Wittgenstein</p>

<p>A meaning of a word is a kind of employment of it. For it is what we learn when the word is incorporated into our language.</p></blockquote>

<p><strong>Words get meaning through use.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>Is there a why? Must I now begin to trust somewhere? That is to say: somewhere I must begin with not-doubting... Wittgenstein</p>

<p>The difficulty is to realize the groundlessness (необоснованность) of our believing.</p></blockquote>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/02/october-02-wednesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-02T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/02/october-02-wednesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Even while we celebrate individualism, we have this tendency to create a situation where individualism results in everybody trying to be an individual in the same way. It creates even more conditions for conformity. <em>Emerson is the enemy of conformity, he is the enemy of imitation.</em></p>

<blockquote><p>Insist on yourself; never imitate.</p></blockquote>

<p>Finding yourself throught action rather than thought a process that aims to discover a foundation or some goal for you entire life. <strong>You are free to recreate every day.</strong> In fact by recreating yourself every day you have this opennes to experience of that can be extraordinarily powerful and conform to no onse else at all.</p>

<h2>Ludwig Wittgenstein</h2>

<p>How language really works when someone's asking for objects in a contruction project and also how we learn languages, how to understand the ways in which our words get meaning.</p>

<blockquote><p>From its seeming to me - or to everyone - to be so, it doesn't follow that it is so. What we can ask is whether it can make sense to doubt it. Ludwig Wittgenstein</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>[humankind] The Direction of History</h2>

<p>People do their work or exchange their goods to money when they trust the figments of the collective imagination. <strong>Trust</strong> is the real raw material from which all types of money in history have been minted.</p>

<p>Money is the most universal and most effictien system of mutual trust ever devised by human beings. How to create trust in money?</p>

<p>The first coins in history, as far as we know, were struck around 640 BC by Kind Elliotus of the kingdom of Lydia (western Turkey).</p>

<p>Religion wants us to believe in something like in God, money doesn't ask us to believe in anything in particular. Money simply asks us to believe that other people believe in something.</p>

<p>Universal principles of money:</p>

<ul>
<li>Universal convertivility</li>
<li>Universal trust</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/01/october-01-tuesday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/10/01/october-01-tuesday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.emersoncentral.com/selfreliance.htm">Self-Reliance by Ralph Waldo Emerson</a></p>

<p>We don't have to wait for something big to happen in our lives, our everyday lives should enliven, should bring the world to life for ourselves and for those around us.</p>

<blockquote><p>The great gift are not got by analysis. Everything good is on the highway.</p></blockquote>

<p>Don't try to analyse whether people are real, whether this experience counts, whether I am authentic, whether I am honest, take to the road, take to life. This notion that <em>everything good is on the highway</em> will inspire American travelers from Woody Guthrie to Jack Kerouac who see that the best thinking is not done behind a desk or in a library, in front of a computer. Everything good is on the highway.</p>

<blockquote><p>Life has no memory. That which proceeds in succession might be remembered, but that which is coexistent, or ejaculated from a deeper cause, as yet far from being conscious knows not its own tendency.</p></blockquote>

<p>Learning from the past is a way of avoiding the present.</p>

<blockquote><p>To believe your own thought, to believe that what is true for you in your private heart is true for all men, - that is genius.</p>

<p>Trust thyself: every heart vibrates to that iron string.</p>

<p>It is easy in the world to live after the world's opinion; it is easy in solitude to live after our own; but the great man is he who in the midst of the crowd keeps with perfect sweetness the independence of solitude.</p>

<p>What I must do is all that concerns me, not what the people think. This rule, equally arduous in actual and in intellectual life, may serve for the whole distinction between greatness and meanness. It is the harder, because you will always find those who think they know what is your duty better than you know it. It is easy in the world to live after the world's opinion; it is easy in solitude to live after our own; but the great man is he who in the midst of the crowd keeps with perfect sweetness the independence of solitude.</p>

<p>Our housekeeping is mendicant, our arts, our occupations, our marriages, our religion, we have not chosen, but society has chosen for us. We are parlour soldiers. We shun the rugged battle of fate, where strength is born.</p></blockquote>

<p>If you don't live ever in a new day, because if you don't live that way, if you are encumbered by your memory, if you are encumbered by the crowd, what will happen is that your will over time become conform more and more to someone else's way of life. You will conform more and more to either the status quo or the dominant majority or even a aggressive minority, but you will be conforming to someone else's mode of life.</p>

<blockquote><p>A foolish consistency is the hobgoblin of little minds, adored by little statesmen and philosophers and divines.</p>

<p>With consistency a great soul has simply nothing to do.</p></blockquote>

<hr />

<h2>[Human Kind] The Direction of History</h2>

<p><strong>History of money</strong></p>

<p>Initially human had no money. Each band hunted and gathered and manufactured almost everything it needed (meat, medicine, sandals and so on). Just on the basis of our personal relationship assuming that one day he will be in trouble or he will need something from me then I will repay the favor which I got from him. It can be also done by simple <em>barter</em>.</p>

<p>Some villages began specializing in producing only one kind of product, let's say olive oil. This had bigger advantages because every village could concentrate on what was the ideal products given its location and climate and topography. Specialization also create new <strong>problems</strong>.</p>

<p>The main problem when different people specialize in different tasks is how exactly to manage exchange of goods and services between all the different specialists.</p>

<p>Barter can never form the basis for a really complex economy. Even if you manage to calculate and to agree how many apples are worth a pair of shoes, barter is not always possible because afterl all, in order to make a barter deal, each sides have to want what the other has got to offer.</p>

<p>Money was created many times in many places in history. It was a purely psychological revolution, the invention of monuments simply the creation of a new imagined reality, of a new inter-subjective reality that exists only in the shared imagination of many people, because money is not coins and money is not bank notes. Money is anything that people are willing to use, in order to represent the value of other things for the purpose of exchanging goods and services. <strong>The value of money depends only on our imagination.</strong></p>

<p>In 2006, the sum total of money in the world was estimated at about $473 trillion and more than 90% of all the money in the world that appear in our bank account, they exist only on computer screens and servers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[[modernart] The Postmodern Everyday]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/september-30-monday/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2013/09/30/september-30-monday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Two person who were important for contemporary philosophy Ralph Waldo Emerson and Ludwin Wittgenstein. Emerson is a key figure in American intellectual history, cultural history, but until pretty recently wasn't seen as a key figure in philosophy. Often flowery (витиеватый) writer, he is a writer of wonderful sentences one of the most quotable authors in American history. Emerson's philosophical contribution to American culture as an author whose importance rivals that of Nietzsche and of Heidegger both of whom were influenced by Emerson.</p>

<p>Emerson was born during the presidency of Thoman Jefferson, so very early in the nineteenth century, lived a long life, he was at some point a minister and left the pulpit, because of a crisis of faith, not so much in the divine being but in instritutionalized religion and became an eassayst and lecturer. Emerson had audiences of thousands of people around the contry who were following his intellectual excursions via lectures in towns across the United States. His departure from enlightenment tradition as it had been imported into the United Stated is really key.</p>

<p><em>The englightenment tradition in the United States was very much indebted to the Lockian Tradition, that is the view that all our ideas come from sensations that we are receptacle of stimuli from the world and that our ideas and then our belief and our work comes as we process the stimulation, the sensation that comes into us. In some ways, thinking of us as a blank slate and having these impressions made upon us by the world.</em> That's the tradition that the American progressive thinkes the beginning of the 19th century adopted.</p>

<p>Emerson has a different view, his view is kind of an activist mind, for him, experience isn't just receiving the world. Emerson's view is that the mind goes out into the world, we make our experience in an active way (something there from Kant). <strong>Experience comes not by just humans being receptacles, but humans creating experience by actively living in the world.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>Grief too will make us idealists. In the death of my son, now more than two years ago, I seem to have lost a beautiful estate, — no more. I cannot get it nearer to me. If tomorrow I should be informed of the bankruptcy of my principal debtors, the loss of my property would be a great inconvenience to me, perhaps, for many years; but it would leave me as it found me, — neither better nor worse. Experience by Ralph Waldo Emerson</p>

<p> Life is a train of moods like a string of beads, and, as we pass through them, they prove to be many-colored lenses which paint the world their own hue, and each shows only what lies in its focus.</p></blockquote>

<p>There are times in our lives when we think that we are living a kind of banal existence. Everything is routine, that you know there, we go to work everyday or we go to school everyday, we have our meals at the same time, we see the same members of our family, our friends, our spouses, our lovers, whatever we're depending on our situation. And after while we've realized we're not feeling things. It's just going thorought life, going through the motions we might say. <strong>And sometimes we want a crisis, you want something big to happen, even if it's a bad thing, because it makes feel more alive, more vital.</strong></p>

<p>If you had some crisis, if you had a grief, you would at least wake up to the world, because you're living in the world without waking up to it. But grief will make us idealists. There are times when we think that we are away from the world and we hope that some huge even happens, even a horrible event, that will make us at least, feel the world.</p>

<p>But in fact, <strong>it's a mistate to think you need some huge experience, some trauma, to wake you up to the world.</strong></p>

<blockquote><p>We animate what we can, and we see only what we animate.</p></blockquote>

<p>We make the world alive to us. We enliven the world.</p>

<hr />

<h2>[Human Kind] The Direction of History</h2>

<p>The interaction between different societies tooks all kind of forms, there were of course wars, trades, immigration from one society to the other, religion missionaries coming from one place to another.</p>

<p><strong>Does human history has a clear direction?</strong></p>

<p>All wars, trades, immigrations in history have a clear general direction and this direction is global unity.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
