<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: practice | Doing things]]></title>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/categories/practice/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-10-02T12:13:03-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://khakimov.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[khakimov]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[First Rails project: Thoughts]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/04/14/first-rails-project-thoughts/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-14T22:06:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/04/14/first-rails-project-thoughts</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Huh, long time no post there. I've been in LA, spent last weekend at the Santa Monica beach, was at few Hollywood clubs, bars and restaurants, drank some wine, beer, white russian and even sake. Whole week was disconnected and didn't touch laptop (confess, only hackernews), so now I'm really ready back to the big fight. So, I came back from airport and in few hours finished my first small project on Rails.</p>

<p><img src="http://distilleryimage6.s3.amazonaws.com/72f5c216810511e1a39b1231381b7ba1_7.jpg" alt="Santa Monica beach" /></p>

<h2>idea</h2>

<p>I just built the place where I can put my thoughts with timeline. Possibly I'll add questions about any sphere of our lives, like <em>"What do you think about love?"</em> or <em>"What do you think about your age?"</em> and look at the progress with my thoughts through time. Everything changing in our world and my thoughts are not exception, so I want to look at the progress and how it is changing. Anyway, first version is <a href="http://hollow-flower-2767.herokuapp.com/users/1/timelines#4">here</a>:</p>

<p><img src="http://pix.am/bJ5h.png" alt="" /></p>

<h2>technology</h2>

<p>I've used js library <a href="http://timeline.verite.co/">timeline</a> as a core and implement it to work with rails.</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li>Full stack:

<ul>
<li>ruby on rails</li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/plataformatec/devise">devise - Flexible authentication solution for Rails</a></li>
<li><a href="http://timeline.verite.co/">timeline js library</a></li>
<li>jquery</li>
<li><a href="http://twitter.github.com/bootstrap/">twitter bootstrap</a></li>
<li>heroku</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<h2>bugs</h2>

<p>Yea, a lot of bugs and roughness with ui, html, css and js. Currently my priority are just code the ruby code and practice with rails and not stuck with js/html/css/design. I'm always thinking about perfection and that was a reason heretofore why I gave up with many ideas and hobbies, I didn't realize one small but very valuable thing - as a beginner you can't do everything perfect. I always compared my code with some opensource project and it was always reason for melancholy, because I though that my code worst ever and I will never able to build something by myself. But the path of trial and error showed me the truth - just practice and focus on one thing.</p>

<h2><a href="http://hollow-flower-2767.herokuapp.com/users/1/timelines#4">My thoughts timeline</a></h2>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Put Off Procrastination]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/03/16/put-off-procrastination/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-16T22:07:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/03/16/put-off-procrastination</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I've already written about idea with <a href="http://pupsor.github.com/blog/2012/03/07/next-idea-for-hacking-with-ruby/">blocker</a> and today I really tired of this and in hour wrote the script which allow you to block facebook, gmail, HN and so on with automatic changing statuses in Skype and Adium (DND).</p>

<p>The project called <a href="https://github.com/pupsor/freodom/">Freodom</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>  Frēodōm is the Old English word for freedom; the state of being free and unconstrained.</p></blockquote>

<p><img src="http://i103.photobucket.com/albums/m151/KiJosh/procrastination.jpg" alt="put
off" /></p>

<ol>
<li>Frēodōm blocks:
  facebook.com,
  news.ycombinator.com,
  reddit.com,
  gmail.com,
  ...</li>
<li>Automatically changes status to DND (skype/adium)</li>
</ol>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Next idea for hacking with Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/03/07/next-idea-for-hacking-with-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-07T13:54:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://khakimov.github.com/blog/2012/03/07/next-idea-for-hacking-with-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Right now I'm sitting at public library of Palo Alto because I have reason. This reason is based on my laziness and totally destructions by anything around me, probably correct word which can describe my problem is procrastination, you can read about  <a href="http://youarenotsosmart.com/2010/10/27/procrastination/">Proctastionation here</a>.</p>

<blockquote><p>  Procrastination is an impulse; it’s buying candy at the checkout. Procrastination is also hyperbolic discounting, taking the sure thing in the present over the caliginous prospect some day far away.</p></blockquote>

<p>So, now you can understand why am I sitting in public library, because this is only one place where I can easily focus and concentrate for doing things or learn to code. Only here I never think about one more cup o tea/coffee or lying to the sofa and think about thinking. But still one bad thing happened here and this thing (I've never thought what I'll able to say this) is internet, to be honest I'm talking about "bad" side of internet like any kind of social networks, AIM, Skype and email.</p>

<p>As you can see those things are our impulse with fast feedback; it's buying candy at the checkout or checking facebook's page, email, twitter, response on each message in Skype and Jabber. To finish my long entry I want to be disconnected for the time when I want to concentrate and focus on current task. But how? Even public library has wi-fi spot. To solve this problem I should disconect myself from the internet or filter it without any "easy" turn off solution, if I want to disconnect for 1 hour - I will and nothing can unblock it except reboot.</p>

<p><img src="http://thejesuswave.files.wordpress.com/2009/03/concentration.gif" alt="Concentrate with Ruby" /></p>

<p>I've seen few apps with same idea, like <a href="http://macfreedom.com/">Freedom</a> that disconect network for a certain time (like have a freedom for 1 hour or 2 hours ;). It costs $10 and works well, but I want to count how many hours I was disconected, maybe try to count how many requests I did to facebook, twitter and how addicted am I and so on.</p>

<p>Few ideas how to do it on mac:</p>

<blockquote><ul>
<li> /etc/hosts</li>
<li> ipfw</li>
<li> just shutdown network interface</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>

<p>to be continue...</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
